<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good hope through grace the jubilee of the kingdom of Christ shall come upon the counterfeit jubilee of Rome, and before the end of the following year 1700, shall begin to bring under desolation that great city and its papacy : therein uniting the year 1697 with 1700 according to prophecy / humbly presented to the faith and prayers of all sincere Protestants by T. Beverley.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37108</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16218760</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16218760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27608)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1087:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good hope through grace the jubilee of the kingdom of Christ shall come upon the counterfeit jubilee of Rome, and before the end of the following year 1700, shall begin to bring under desolation that great city and its papacy : therein uniting the year 1697 with 1700 according to prophecy / humbly presented to the faith and prayers of all sincere Protestants by T. Beverley.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Marshall ... and John Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 70.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XVIII, 7-8 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Prophecies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GOOD HOPE THROUGH GRACE.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jubilee</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt ſhall come upon the Counterfeit <hi>Jubilee</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and before the end of the Following Year 1700<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall begin to bring under Deſolation that <hi>Great City</hi> and its <hi>Papacy:</hi> Therein Uniting the Year 1697 with 1700. accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly Preſented to the Faith and Prayers of all Sincere <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By, <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rev. xviii. xix.</bibl> 
               <hi>In one Hour is ſhe made Deſolate.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Marſhall,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Newgate-Street,</hi> and <hi>John Marſhall,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:3"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE His much Honoured Sir <hi>Samuel Barnardiſton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough I muſt ever Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a long Series of very great Obligations to your Friendſhip, and Favour for me; Yet That is not the Sole, nor ſo much as the Principal Reaſon of the preſenting this following Diſcourſe to your Acceptance: The more Due Reaſons of that are, That by the Freedoms you have Allowed me of Converſation with you; I have very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Evidences of your ſincere Love to the Kingdom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the <hi>Lord of Glory;</hi> in its preſent Spiritual
<pb facs="tcp:105101:4"/> Evangelical Adminiſtration; and in its Gradual Illuſtrations of it ſelf in Glory, Promiſed and Foretold to the latter Days. And yet more particularly, as in All Things I had obſerved, your <hi>Patriottal</hi> Spirit, your Great <hi>Love</hi> to your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, the true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spirit; ſo your Great <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> and Bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That no Greater <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> could be procured, for the Suffering <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> beyond the Seas, and particularly in <hi>France.</hi> But I hope God ſupports you in ſo long a Life, to ſee the Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his <hi>Kingdom.</hi> And That your Honourable <hi>Lady,</hi> whom I have long obſerved the Trueſt <hi>Conſort</hi> of All the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties, that God hath been pleaſed to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſate to you, may Rejoyce with you in that ſo Great Joy, is the Humble Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prayer of, Moſt Honour'd Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Affectionate Humble Servant in our Great Lord, <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The PREFACE to the Favourable</hi> Proteſtant READER.</head>
            <p>THE Diſcourſe following, I Humbly Preſent, as the Reſult of the moſt Cloſe Reſearches into the <hi>Sure Word</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> after the ſo great Diſappointment of the Hopes I had at the Year <hi>Ninety Seven.</hi> I Humbly Acknowledge to Infinite Grace, it gave me not the leaſt Doubt of the Truth and Divine Authority of ſacred Scripture, or particularly of the <hi>Prophetic Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> which the Divine Spirit takes ſuch care to aſſure, Are the <hi>True Sayings of God,</hi> and that <hi>Theſe Sayings</hi> are <hi>Faithful</hi> and <hi>True;</hi> And I Humbly Bleſs Him, I have beſides all thoſe Great and Weighty Arguments, that ſo many Holy and Learned Men have Eſtabliſhed the <hi>Autopiſty,</hi> or ſelf-evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Divineſs of Scripture upon, I have the particular Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſo Admirable a <hi>Prophetic</hi> Scheme and Frame; God hath given me, that I am ſure none, but <hi>Infinite Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> could ever have Projected, or ſo curiouſly have Wrought and Inlaid; and only to be Found by Compare of one <hi>Prophetic</hi> Scripture with another, and when they are ſo matched one with another, the Admirable <hi>Artifice</hi> is ſeen.</p>
            <p>Now this very Adorable Workmanſhip led me to <hi>Ninety Seven</hi> by <hi>Prophetic Iconiſms,</hi> or Images, adjuſted to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetic</hi> Numbers of Time, and juſtified and verified by Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact, or as <hi>Prophecy</hi> calls them, <hi>Effects</hi> of <hi>Viſion</hi> in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez.</hi> 12. 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the Matter of Fact of Viſion.</hi>
               </note> univerſal <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and <hi>Chronology,</hi> Correſponding to them.</p>
            <p>And in the very laſt Year, after all Hope ſeeming to be paſt, it pleaſed the Lord to ſhew me that Character of Time, ſtiled, <hi>Indictions</hi> or <hi>Fifteens</hi> of <hi>Years;</hi> even ſtudiouſly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in adding 2 and 3 Fifteens to 1260, made up of ſo exact <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.</note> Fifteens; making them, 1290; 1345; All which ſure could never be by Chance. This Note of Indiction, I ſay, what I had always accounted, I found enclapſed, whole <hi>Prophetic</hi> Time, from <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Death to the <hi>Bleſſed</hi> Time at the
<pb facs="tcp:105101:5"/> end of the 1335 Days, all which make 2730 Days <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Indicted; As any one verſed in Accomptancy may eaſily find. And the very firſt, the 390 Days of <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s bearing <hi>Judah</hi>'s Sin, begin in ſet <hi>Indictions.</hi> Hereby I have found <hi>Ninety Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> eſtabliſhed by even <hi>Arithmetic</hi> Demonſtration, as I have made out in a Treatiſe on purpoſe, Printed 1699.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon all this, I could not remove from <hi>Ninety Seven;</hi> However, ſo great a Failure looked ſo unfavourably upon it: What therefore God, upon earneſt unwearied Prayers, and ſo ſtrict Enquiry, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Holy Oracle,</hi> was pleaſed to give in the Night at the Houſe of an <hi>Elect Lady,</hi> near <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risbury;</hi> and to enable to Cultivate and Improve; I have here given to public view, conſiſting of Four Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Certainty of a moſt Stupendious Judgment, to be executed on ſome City, deſcyphered by <hi>Babylon,</hi> and this City proved to be <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Time of this Judgment to be executed, is at ſome pompous Time of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Holy Year</hi> or <hi>Jubilee,</hi> and great Princes appearing for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That whereas the Time this Judgment to be Executed, was moſt properly <hi>Ninety Seven;</hi> there is by a curious Artifice of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> a Reſerve of 3 <hi>Years</hi> and a half, reaching to 1700: With an Anſwer of Objections to ſearch of Time from Miſtakes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſuch a Reſerve is called God's <hi>Infraction</hi> or <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>Promiſe,</hi> or his <hi>Abruption,</hi> and Breaking off the <hi>Series</hi> and Contexture of Begun Providences; the Notions of which are opened and applied to the preſent Caſe; there are alſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves in a way of Wiſdom and Goodneſs, from <hi>Ninety Seven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all recommended to Faith and Prayer, under Divine Bleſſing; and Humbly laid at the Feet of the Supreme <hi>Palmoni,</hi> or <hi>Wonderful Numberer</hi> of Time, the <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyptes</hi> or <hi>Revealer,</hi> the <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> or Man <hi>Cloathed in Linnen,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of our <hi>Profeſſion;</hi> That He may judge, whether his Word or not. To Him, God over all, Bleſſed for ever, be Glory for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105101:5"/>
            <head>THE JUBILEE OF THE Kingdom of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> Coming on the Counterfeit JUBILEE of <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Rev. xviii. vii. viii.</bibl>
               <q>She ſaith in her Heart, I ſit a Queen, and am no Widow, and ſhall ſee no Sorrow. Therefore ſhall her Plagues come in one day, Death, and Mourning, and Famine; and ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with Fire; for ſtrong is the Lord who judgeth her.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Intention of the following Diſcourſe, is to give Encouragement from this Scripture firſt; then, to excite and even arouſe the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Zeal, Faith and Hope; and to oblige the earneſt Prayers and Supplications of the <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches and Nations; and humbly to beſeech the Princes and Governments of them, by their Commands and Examples ſo to lead the way, that we may all <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 10.</note> cry out with the <hi>loud Voice</hi> of the <hi>Souls under</hi> the <hi>Altar; How long Lord, Holy</hi> and <hi>True, doſt Thou not avenge the Blood of thy Servants; on Them, who dwell on the Earth!</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105101:6"/> which is a Prophetick <hi>Periphraſe</hi> of <hi>Pagan Rome</hi> firſt, and then of <hi>Rome Antichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this at a Time, whereunto the Divine Spirit hath directed us ſo plainly, and ſpecially to look for it; as at a proper Seaſon God hath foreſcen, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out for the Execution of his Judgment on <hi>Babylon;</hi> even this her Enchanting <hi>Jubilee,</hi> when ſhe ſays, <hi>I ſit a Queen;</hi> I am now on a Throne giving out my Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons and Indulgences: <hi>I am no Widow, nor ſhall know the lofs of Children;</hi> Behold from all Parts, how they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about me at this very time!</p>
            <p>And at the time of ſo violent a Perſecution upon the Servants of God, making the ſame <hi>Proteſtation</hi> with our ſelves againſt the <hi>Papal</hi> Idolatry, Superſtitions and Tyranny.</p>
            <p>If we are not concern'd at ſuch a time as this, we <hi>have</hi> only a <hi>Name</hi> to <hi>live,</hi> as, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,</hi> but <hi>are dead;</hi> as God Charges upon the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Sardis,</hi> the <hi>Prophetical Emblem</hi> of the <hi>Churches</hi> ſtiled the <hi>Reformed;</hi> We have forgotten, how we <hi>Received</hi> and <hi>Heard,</hi> in that ſo great Appearance of God, by the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 1, 2.</note> firſt <hi>Reformers;</hi> and Princes will too ſadly ſeem to have loſt that firſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which acted thoſe Princes in the Tranſactions at <hi>Spire Am.</hi> 1529. Oh that therefore we might <hi>Remember, Hold faſt</hi> and <hi>Repent:</hi> And if there were <hi>a Spirit pour'd out from on high</hi> upon us, a Spirit of <hi>Prayer,</hi> who knows but that in the midſt of this falſe <hi>Jubilee; Theſe two things, Widowhood</hi> and <hi>loſs of Children,</hi> Alienation of Princes and People, might come on this <hi>Myſtic Babel</hi> in <hi>one Day,</hi> in <hi>one Moment!</hi> If we could <hi>wreſtle with God,</hi> as <hi>Jacob,</hi> theſe <hi>Two Things</hi> would <hi>certainly come</hi> upon Her in <hi>their Perfection,</hi> as on <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 47. 8.</note> that <hi>Babylon</hi> of Old, for the <hi>Multitude</hi> of her <hi>Sorceries</hi> and <hi>Enchantments</hi> in this very day of her <hi>Jubilee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:6"/>
            <p> To this very purpoſe, I will draw out from the Text, as it ſtands in connexion with This, the Former, the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chapters, Six great <hi>Propoſitions;</hi> and then argue further upon them in compare with other Scripture <hi>Prophecies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition</hi> 1. There is undeniably a great Judgment denounced by God, and largely deſcribed upon ſome <hi>City,</hi> Figured by <hi>Babylon the Great,</hi> that muſt moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be Executed in its own Time, and upon the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deſigned, according to the <hi>ſure word of Prophecy,</hi> Cap. 1. 1. <hi>The Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that <hi>God gave to him,</hi> to <hi>ſhew to his Servants things ſhortly,</hi> that is, with great ſpeed; from that very time it was given; to <hi>come to paſs</hi> ſucceſſively; till the <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in compariſon of which all time <hi>is ſhort:</hi> Now becauſe this Judgment cannot yet (as will appear) be poſſibly ſuppoſed to have come to <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.</note> paſs, it muſt yet come to paſs: And becauſe ſo much hath all along, and for ſo very long time been <hi>coming to paſs,</hi> according to this <hi>Prophecy;</hi> and yet this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath not been Executed, the Execution of it muſt needs therefore be very near.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 2. There are Infallible Characters fixed by the <hi>Prophecy</hi> in theſe Chapters before us, on the the <hi>City</hi> ſo denounced upon; aſſuring this <hi>City</hi> is the preſent <hi>Papal Rome.</hi> For if <hi>Rome</hi> be the <hi>City</hi> Characteriz'd, as it is now <hi>Papal,</hi> it is that <hi>City</hi> ſo threatned by this Judgment; For the Characters, and the Judgment are inſeparable; Now <hi>Rome</hi> will appear to be the City Characteriz'd, and therefore on it muſt the <hi>Judgment</hi> here <hi>written</hi> be <hi>Executed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. It is one of the great Glories of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that the firſt coming of it into Execution ſhall be with great ſuddenneſs and ſurprizal; and when ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Few</hi> (ſtiled by Chriſt the <hi>Few Names</hi> in <hi>Sardis)</hi> have a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105101:7"/> Thought, or Apprehenſion of any ſuch thing: <hi>One Day, one Hour, one Moment,</hi> as of Ancient <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſpeak the very great Velocity of the Judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 4. The Princes, that at this time Bear up the Grandeur and the Haughtineſs of <hi>Papal Rome,</hi> by <hi>giving their Power</hi> and <hi>Kingdom to the Beaſt;</hi> called therefore <hi>His Horns,</hi> ſhall be by <hi>the Lamb, King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords</hi> ſo <hi>overcome,</hi> as to be made Inſtruments in the Execution of the Judgment in ſuch Parts, and Degrees, as the <hi>ſtrong Lord, who Judgeth,</hi> ſhall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion them unto; which ſhall highly Exalt, and make Illuſtrious the Judgment: As an Indication of this, it is ſaid <hi>C.</hi> 17. 16. <hi>The Kings ſhall hate the Whore; ſhall make her Deſolate, and ſhell eat her Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>ſhall burn her with Fire;</hi> and in this Text, her <hi>Plagues</hi> are <hi>Death,</hi> and one concurring with the other <hi>Mourning, Famine,</hi> and <hi>burning with Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 5. The Greatneſs and the ſudden Invaſion of this Judgment, as denounced by God, are uncontroula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to be demonſtrated, not only as to the poſſibility, but the certainty of both; as from the Truth of the Lord, who hath ſo long ago denounced it, ſo from the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Omnipotency of the <hi>ſtrong Lord</hi> that <hi>judgeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 6. The Divine Preſcience and Wiſdom, hath choſen out a Time, and decreed it for the Execution of this <hi>Judgment,</hi> when <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall ſhew it ſelf in its Pride, its Pomp, its Preſumption, Security; For it is, when ſhe ſhall ſay, <hi>I ſit a Queen,</hi> and <hi>ſhall ſee no Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row;</hi> and 'tis moſt undeniable its <hi>Jubilee</hi> is ſuch a Time, and when Great Princes ſhall ſo be at her Devotion, as for her ſake, with ſuch a violence to perſecute, and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes ſtand by, and have nothing to ſay againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. I begin with the firſt Propoſition; that the Judgment here forewritten muſt moſt certainly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted:
<pb facs="tcp:105101:7"/> That there is a great Judgment here deſcribed and denounced on ſome <hi>City,</hi> Figur'd by <hi>Babylon the Great,</hi> is moſt unconteſtable; every word in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going and this Chapter aſſures it; and in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapter, we have moſt ſolemn <hi>Doxologies</hi> and Thankſgivings upon it; In <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. 1. The <hi>Viſion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins thus; <hi>John</hi> is called to come to the <hi>Angel,</hi> who would ſhew him the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Great Whore:</hi> In this <hi>C.</hi> 18. 1. <hi>Another Angel</hi> having <hi>Great Power,</hi> and with whoſe <hi>Glory</hi> the <hi>Earth ſhone</hi> Appears; and he <hi>cry'd mightily with a loud Voice, Babylon the great is fallen, is fallen;</hi> certainly and irrecoverably <hi>Fallen;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Viſion</hi> goes on in the moſt dreadful Expreſſions, and Pourtraies of a Judgment moſt ſtupendious: <hi>The Kings of the Earth bewail,</hi> and <hi>ſtand afar off for fear of her Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> her <hi>Merchants throw Duſt on their Heads,</hi> and <hi>cry out</hi> in their Lamentings, <hi>Alas! Alas!</hi> and at laſt her Irrecoverable Ruin is ſet out by a <hi>Millſtone, caſt into the bottom of the Sea</hi> by a <hi>mighty Angel</hi> pronouncing; So ſhall <hi>Babylon</hi> be <hi>thrown down,</hi> and <hi>found no more at all,</hi> ver. 15. 19. 21.</p>
            <p>If this <hi>Judgment</hi> then be <hi>Prophetically</hi> denounced by the Holy, the True, the Mighty God; It muſt and ſhall certainly come to paſs in the Time, and upon the <hi>City</hi> deſigned: This is a Principle of Natural Light and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual Reaſon ſo clear, I ſhall no further inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>What then can be levied by way of Objection? I can poſſibly ſuppoſe but two Things: Either the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> muſt be called in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to queſtion, as not from God; or it muſt be ſaid, the <hi>Judgment</hi> hath been already Executed.</p>
            <div n="1" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. As to the firſt, I ſhall ſay theſe three Things.</head>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105101:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That this <hi>Book</hi> hath ſuch a Majeſty of Truth in the moſt awfull Repreſentations of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being, of the Redemption of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, of the Beauty of Holineſs, and of the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs and dreadful end of Sin; That whoever hath any Fear of God ariſing from the light of Natural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or any Guſt of the Excellency of Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, cannot but acknowledge it from God: Add hereunto thoſe bright Rays, that ſhining from it, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where enlighten the Purity of Divine Worſhip, in deteſtation of all Idolatry and Superſtition; and Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate the Glory of <hi>Martyrdom, for keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, and for holding the Teſtimony of Jeſus:</hi> In all, The Glory of it, is as of the <hi>Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> given to him by God; and who then will dare to ſet himſelf as a mark for that Commination; <hi>If any Man take from the Words of the Prophecy</hi> of this <hi>Book,</hi> God will <hi>take away his Part</hi> from all the great Promiſes of it, and will add to him the <hi>Plagues written</hi> in it; which both are moſt dreadful. <hi>C.</hi> 22. 18, 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Let any one conſider the Curious and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable <hi>Iconiſms, Images</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> found in this <hi>Book;</hi> and if he haue <hi>a Mind,</hi> that hath <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> to apply them to the Events foretold from their firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſhortly, <hi>that is,</hi> to begin from the time of giving it, immediately to come to paſs, and reaching down to this very time, he will find them ſo exactly to anſwer the <hi>prophetical</hi> and predictory <hi>Types;</hi> as to juſtifie this Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> to be from God, by that very demonſtration of Divinity God appeals to <hi>Eſay</hi> 41, 23. <hi>Shew us things to come, that we may know ye are Gods;</hi> Hence therefore we may be aſſur'd of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> even from the preſcience of God in it.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105101:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. The <hi>Prophecies</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> in <hi>Iſa. C.</hi> 47. and <hi>Jerem.</hi> 51. and in <hi>Daniel</hi> throughout, are ſuch an Exemplar of Judgment, on whatever ſhall come under the Name of <hi>Babylon the great,</hi> (as <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> memorializ'd it for after Ages,) that if we are duly perſwaded of the Divine Authority of the one, we have all the juſt Inducements of the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of this <hi>Apochaliptic Prophecy;</hi> and that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, who breathed the one, breathed the other alſo; who foreſaw <hi>Myſtical Babylon</hi> in litteral, and prepar'd the Shades of the Deſtruction of it, the Latter in the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; which highly aggrandizes the Evidence of the Divine Authority of the <hi>Revelation:</hi> For none but the Divine Underſtanding could ever have excogitated ſuch an Admirable Agreement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2. As to the ſecond Objection, That the <hi>Judgment</hi> hath been already Executed, and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> fulfilled, it ſhall be anſwer'd under the ſecond Poſition; that the <hi>City,</hi> which is here denounced upon, is <hi>Papal Rome,</hi> from whence it will neceſſarily follow, It is not, nor can can yet have been Executed; becauſe the City <hi>Rome</hi> is yet in Being and Greatneſs, but by this Judgment is utterly to be deſtroyed; But in the mean time, it may be envinc'd, from the glorious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, drawn out <hi>C.</hi> 19. <hi>C.</hi> 20. <hi>C.</hi> 21. <hi>C.</hi> 22. which are ſo cloſe connexed with this Judgment, which have not yet come into effect, that therefore not the <hi>Judgment</hi> itſelf; for who can apprehend ſuch Glorious Appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as the <hi>Heavens opening,</hi> Chriſt's coming forth At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with the <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> ſuch an Univerſal Conqueſt of Enemies, and ſuch a <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and Illuſtrious ſtate of it, have ever enlightned a World continuing yet ſo dark! He that can perſwade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to believe that, may believe any thing moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable: I come therefore to the ſecond Poſition.</head>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105101:9"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Poſit.</hi> 2. There are Infallible Characters fixed by this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> by which we may be moſt aſſur'd, It is the preſent <hi>Papal Rome</hi> to be Judg'd; For the making out this Poſition, Two things are to be prov'd.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf is the <hi>City</hi> intended.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That though <hi>Rome Pagan</hi> be intended, yet <hi>Rome Papal</hi> is the <hi>Babylon,</hi> on which the Judgment is to be Executed, ſo fully here deſcrib'd: That it is <hi>Rome,</hi> There are two undeniable, even Litteral Affirmations; that even the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Expoſitors, who have ſo great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ward off the Blow from <hi>Rome,</hi> yet they have not the face to deny, the <hi>City</hi> muſt needs be <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore ſome of them fix on <hi>Pagan Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Rome,</hi> take it <hi>Pagan,</hi> take it <hi>Papal; Rome</hi> it ſelf is the <hi>City</hi> to be thus <hi>Judg'd,</hi> as the Divine Spirit hath made known to us by ſaying, the <hi>Seven H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ads</hi> are <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Mountains</hi> on which the <hi>Woman ſitteth;</hi> Now the <hi>Seven Headed City,</hi> was as plain a Character of <hi>Rome,</hi> when the <hi>Apocalyptick</hi> Apoſtle writ, as if we deſcribed <hi>London</hi> by the <hi>City,</hi> whoſe Shore the <hi>Thames</hi> waſhes, or <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by the <hi>Boſphorus</hi> coming up to it.</p>
               <p>Again, the ſame Divine Spirit hath told us, the <hi>City</hi> is ſhe that hath the (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) Kingdom at this very preſent time over the <hi>Kings of the Earth;</hi> which is as plain a Diſtinction of <hi>Rome,</hi> as at the time of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> given, as if we deſcrib'd <hi>London</hi> by the <hi>City;</hi> where the Courts of the King, of Judicature, and the Councils of the Nation are, and the chief Seat of Trade is; or <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by the <hi>Ottoman Port:</hi> Who that knows the Hiſtory of the World at that time, knows not; That <hi>Rome</hi> was the Seate of the Empire of the World at that very Time: This being ſo plain, though other Proofs may be given, I paſs off from it, and come to the ſecond part of the Poſition; That though <hi>Pagan Rome</hi> is to be taken in, yet <hi>Papal Rome</hi> is the <hi>City</hi> to be <hi>Judg'd,</hi> eſpecially, Ultimately, Finally.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105101:9"/>
               <p> That this may be made out, I muſt lay in the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; That, as the <hi>City Rome</hi> is Evidently ſhewn to be the <hi>Babylon,</hi> to be Judg'd; So the Supremacy meant here, by the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> muſt be a <hi>Supremacy</hi> cloſely Related to the <hi>City Rome,</hi> and Bearing up that <hi>City</hi> in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Grandeur; as <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the place of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other of the <hi>Supreme Magiſtracys</hi> of it. For the <hi>City,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that Carryes it, are Inſeparable; If it be therefore made out that the <hi>Supremacy</hi> is <hi>Papal,</hi> on which the <hi>City</hi> is Born up when it is Judged; It will moſt certainly follow, that the <hi>City</hi> to be <hi>Judg'd,</hi> is <hi>Rome Papal;</hi> Even as if it be prov'd, that the <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>Judg'd,</hi> is <hi>Rome Papal;</hi> It is therein prov'd that the <hi>Supremacy Judg'd</hi> is <hi>Papal Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> For as is ſaid; They are Inſeparable and Proportion'd one to another: I will therefore draw out ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Characters of <hi>Papal Supremacy,</hi> and of <hi>Papal Rome,</hi> that are moſt Plain Matters of Fact upon both, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to, and Compare one with another, and that are given in <hi>Prophecy</hi> upon each, as the moſt plain and eaſy to be underſtood (waving what is more <hi>Critical</hi> and Curious,) and yet moſt Argumentative and moſt Concluſive, as laid one to another, conſider'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that <hi>Papal Rome,</hi> with its <hi>Papacy,</hi> are here Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to be <hi>Judged.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Characters are theſe Following.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charact.</hi> 1. It is undeniable, The <hi>Papacy</hi> lays claim to a <hi>Supremacy,</hi> as the <hi>Vicar of Chriſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop, Pope of Rome;</hi> as Univerſal as <hi>Emperor</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore over the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Europe;</hi> and a <hi>Paſtor</hi> above Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the <hi>Supreme</hi> Powers here <hi>upon Earth;</hi> So the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Catholic Church,</hi> The Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs of Churches, or <hi>Lady,</hi> as <hi>Babylon</hi> of <hi>Old;</hi> or as <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105101:10"/> when <hi>Miſtreſs, Lady</hi> of the World; All this is undeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Matter of Fact in general knowledg of the World at this day; and much more ſo before the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what more plain in Prophecy! In <hi>Daniel,</hi> in this <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation; Beaſt</hi> is Interpreted into <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as a Succeſſion of <hi>Kings; Having Times</hi> and <hi>Laws given into his Hand</hi> to <hi>Change. Horns</hi> are <hi>Kings,</hi> and ſo muſt the <hi>Little Horn</hi> be, and as more <note place="margin">Dan. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Stout then his Fellows,</hi> an <hi>Imperial</hi> King: In this <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the <hi>Eighth King,</hi> and of the Seven <hi>Heads, Supremes</hi> over <hi>Rome.</hi> To ſhew his <hi>Imperialneſs, Ten Kings</hi> are as <hi>Horns</hi> upon his <hi>Head,</hi> in Subordination to him: <hi>Power</hi> was <hi>given</hi> to him <hi>over all Kindreds,</hi> and <hi>Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Nations;</hi> An <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 13. 7. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 17. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>City,</hi> it is <hi>Babylon The Great, the Great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>I ſit a Queen.</hi> As ſhe had <hi>ſate</hi> upon <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor Kings,</hi> ſo ſhe is <hi>Carried</hi> on high by the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> The <hi>Kings of the Earth Live Deliciouſly with her,</hi> her <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> are the <hi>Great Men,</hi> the Grandees of the <hi>Earth</hi> made <hi>Rich</hi> by her <hi>Coſtlyneſs;</hi> And the Greatneſs and Variety of her <hi>Merchandiſe</hi> ſpeaks her Greatneſs; Now ſeeing it hath been Proved by the Letter of the <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Rome</hi> is the <hi>Seven Headed City,</hi> that was <hi>Imperial</hi> at the Time of the <hi>Prophecy</hi> given: I appeal to all Perſons who know the State of Things now in <hi>Europe,</hi> and what it was in Ancient Time; whether there be in the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> that then was, any Supreme like the now <hi>Pope</hi> for Univerſality; For not only the Kings, (excepting thoſe who Renounced him in the <hi>Reformation)</hi> but even he is who called <hi>Emperor,</hi> is no <hi>Emperor,</hi> in Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>Papal Supreme,</hi> whom he himſelf owns, and payes Subjection to; or any <hi>City</hi> that can pretend to be a <hi>Queen,</hi> as <hi>Rome</hi> pretends to be; as it calls it ſelf
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105101:10"/> the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi> There can be no pretence of the <hi>Otoman Supreme,</hi> or of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> like it, Though that be ſo fixed as it is, as a Spightful Rival of it by the hand of Vengeance, as might be further ſhewn, if Seaſonable now: And therefore this Character, I look, upon, even Demonſtratively Diſtinctive of <hi>Papal Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Papal Supremacy:</hi> But if this can be thought not ſufficient, what follows will more aſſure it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charact.</hi> 2. The <hi>Papal Supremacy,</hi> However Preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent it hath been, and is; is yet in the Ballance of Worldly Powers, a weak, Precarious, Impuiſſant <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy;</hi> and hath no <hi>Martial</hi> Strength to ſupport or Defend it ſelf by; as is well known in all Hiſtory and Daily Experience; So that Great Stateſmen <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puffendors Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Hiſtor. of</hi> Europ. <hi>Cap</hi> 12.</note> and <hi>Politicians</hi> have been much Amuſed; How ſo Unarm'd a <hi>Supremacy</hi> ſhould have ſo long continued it ſelf; We in this Nation are Witneſſes, how Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulably the <hi>King</hi> of this Nation <hi>(Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> at his own Pleaſure) Revuls'd himſelf and it from him; and <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> after the Reſumbmiſion of <hi>Queen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Abdicated the <hi>Papacy</hi> anew, as other Princes about the ſame Time did.</p>
               <p>In the ſame manner let us Judg of the <hi>City Rome</hi> now; and we know it is not the Reſidence of the Ancient <hi>Martial</hi> Spirit, and Proweſs that Inhabited it; But, as its <hi>Supreme,</hi> is Unarm'd, ſo is the <hi>City</hi> upheld by the Kindneſs of the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> that ſhall <hi>Hate</hi> and Famiſh, and <hi>Burn</hi> it hereafter; and by the Fraud and Cunning of the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Cardinals</hi> and other the Preiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of it; an Imperial City in a <hi>Myſtery;</hi> that is a <hi>Falſe Catholick Church</hi> held up by Art.</p>
               <p>Let us obſerve now, How <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſpeaks of this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, both as to the <hi>City,</hi> and as to its <hi>Supreme;</hi> and we ſhall find in <hi>Daniel;</hi> The <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes</hi> of the <hi>Image, Dan.</hi> 2. Which make the laſt State of the <hi>Fourth Roman</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105101:11"/> 
                  <hi>Monarchy</hi> or Kingdom, were <hi>Part</hi> of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Part</hi> of <hi>Clay;</hi> Partly <hi>Strong</hi> as <hi>Iron,</hi> and Part <hi>Broken Fragile v.</hi> 42. <hi>Weak</hi> and <hi>Frail</hi> as <hi>Clay.</hi> And what could the whole Ingeny of Man have found out more Curious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet Significantly to Expreſs the Feeble <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi> of the <hi>Papacy;</hi> Like <hi>Feet</hi> of <hi>Clay</hi> upheld by the <hi>Iron</hi> of the <hi>Ten Kings;</hi> and in the other <hi>Viſion</hi> the <hi>Ten Horns</hi> Surround and Cover the Little <hi>Horn,;</hi> that elſe could not defend it ſelf; his <hi>Power</hi> ſhall be <hi>Mighty,</hi> but not in his own <hi>Power, C.</hi> 8. 24. In the <hi>Revelation</hi> the <hi>Beaſts Supremacy</hi> is continually Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with an <hi>Image;</hi> Conioyn'd with a <hi>Spiritual Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Supremacy, which is a <hi>Supremacy in an Image:</hi> And it is by Gift under a Divine <hi>Decree,</hi> The <hi>Ten Kings Agree,</hi> and with <hi>One Conſent give their Kingdom, and Power, and Strength to the Beaſt:</hi> It is by Gift, and by Agreement, and as by Ballance on One Another's Power, as Event hath prov'd.</p>
               <p>Let us now behold the Character drawn by <hi>Prophecy,</hi> in relation to the <hi>City; She ſits</hi> indeed <hi>a Queen;</hi> But it is by the <hi>Sorcery</hi> of a Falſe Religion, <hi>upon Princes and People,</hi> by making them drunk with the <hi>Wine</hi> of her <hi>Fornication</hi> and <hi>Adulteries;</hi> an Impure, Senſeleſs ſort of Devotion, and the Falſe Hopes of Salvation by it; a Drunken Dream fit to Enchant, and Enſlave thoſe who are bereaved of All Judicious Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſtianity; and pleas'd with a Faith, Worſhip of God, and Converſation, ſuited only to a Carnal Senſuality: All this ſhews us wherein the Strength of this <hi>City,</hi> or Falſe Church lies.</p>
               <p>And how Exactly do theſe Things Anſwer One An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other! What we Every Day ſee with our Eyes, and hear with our Ears, and have all manner of Aſſurance of in <hi>Papal Rome;</hi> and theſe Delineations of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> carrying us out of all manner of Doubt, that the <hi>City</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105101:11"/> here deſcribed to be <hi>Judg'd,</hi> is <hi>Papal Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Char.</hi> 3. In the <hi>Papacy of Rome,</hi> and its <hi>City,</hi> or Falſe Church, we find the Collection of All the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions and Idolatries, that ever have been (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, if not altogether) in the World, under One Pretence, Colour, and Coverture, or other; Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning like Filthy Drains, into this Foul Great Sewer; enough to fill Volumes with their incredible Multitude and Variety; Such as if duly conſider'd, cannot but be thought moſt Strange and Horrid, in ſo Divine, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and ſo Intellectual a Worſhip of God, as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity teaches.</p>
               <p>And how hath Prophecy Repreſented this! In <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> by the Infamous Name of <hi>Beaſt,</hi> common to Him, with other Idolatrous Pagan Supremes; So by His thinking to change <hi>Times and Laws given into his Hand</hi> for ſuch a Term, plainly ſignifying Sovereign Power, Engaging it ſelf in the Deviſing and Introducing Falſe Religion, as <hi>Jeroboam</hi> of old, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> c. 12. 32. 38.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Revelation</hi> He is <hi>Full of the Names of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi> that is, of Idolatry: For ſo the Idolatry of ſuch as make a Profeſſion of the True God, is ſtyled, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 7. by the Judgment of the moſt Learned Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: And indeed it can be no other; For to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a Beeing ſo Holy, Wiſe; <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the Eternal, Infinite Spirit; and then to put upon him the Folly, and <hi>Nothing,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſtyles it, of an <hi>Idol,</hi> is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo it is to arrogate to be worſhipp'd with him; And it is moſt obſervable, the <hi>Revelation</hi> frequently Joyns this <hi>Beaſt Worſhipp'd,</hi> and his <hi>Image Worſhipp'd,</hi> plainly importing his <hi>Idolatrouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105101:12"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Aholah,</hi> and <hi>Aholibah,</hi> thoſe Idolatrous Churches of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> are a moſt <hi>Graphical</hi> Deſcription of this <hi>City,</hi> or Falſe Church, in the ſame Kind of Style; <hi>Aholah</hi> and <hi>Aholibah,</hi> were ſet out, <hi>Ezek.</hi> c. 23. in all the <hi>Lewdneſs</hi> of <hi>Infamous Women;</hi> Thoſe Falſe Churches of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah;</hi> if it be Lawful at all to uſe the Name of Churches in their Caſe, and particularly <hi>Judah</hi> have the Title of an <hi>Imperious,</hi> or, as it may be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd exactly to the preſent Caſe, <hi>Imperial Whoriſh Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> Ezek. 16. 33. So <hi>Rome</hi> is Pictur'd having in her <hi>Hand a Golden Cup, full of the Wine of her Fornication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charact.</hi> 4. That which is ſo Generally to be obſerv'd in the <hi>Papacy,</hi> is the very Height of a moſt Bold, <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous</hi> Arrogancy: The very <hi>Supremacy</hi> he uſurps in the Chriſtian Church, ſhews his <hi>Luciferian Pride.</hi> The Title, HIS HOLINESS, is moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious, Seeing God <hi>Only Holy</hi> is, much more <hi>Alone Holineſs</hi> it ſelf: His Claim of Infallibility above Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, is a ſmall Thing; for he exalts it above Scripture it ſelf; That (in the Senſe of the very <hi>Phariſees)</hi> Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous taking upon him to <hi>Pardon Sin,</hi> his <hi>Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> Pretended Deliverances from <hi>Purgatory,</hi> his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſeit <hi>Miracles,</hi> his <hi>Anathematiſing</hi> and Curſing down All to Hell, who deteſt his Idolatries, ſhews him that <hi>Proud</hi> and <hi>Haughty Scorner,</hi> who <hi>Deals in Proud Wrath:</hi> His ſetting his Throne, and Lifting his Scepter above the Thrones and Scepters of Princes, is moſt Horrid, and Intolerable Inſolency: In All this the <hi>City</hi> is one with him, <hi>ſitting</hi> alought upon him, and Born upon him in all this <hi>Babyloniſh Lucifertaniſm.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 14. 12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let us obſerve, how Scripture-Predictions ſhew this his Sathanic Preſumption; <hi>Daniel</hi> calls it <hi>his ſpeaking</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105101:12"/> 
                  <hi>Words,</hi> High, Great <hi>Words againſt the Moſt High;</hi> c. 7. 25. <hi>Standing up againſt the Prince of Princes,</hi> c. 8. 25. <hi>Speaking marvellous things againſt the God of Gods;</hi> and <hi>He ſhall magnify Himſelf above every God,</hi> or Supreme: <hi>c.</hi> 11. 36. <hi>He ſitteth in the Temple of God as God, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf he is God. He exalts himſelf above All that is called God;</hi> (the Scripture Expreſſion for <hi>Princes)</hi> or that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is ſtyled <hi>Auguſt;</hi> taken from the Name of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> the Greateſt of <hi>Rome's Emperors;</hi> and become at that Time the <hi>Imperial Title:</hi> Thus the Apoſtle deſcribes the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> calling him the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> in the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy,</hi> he was deſcribing; and that we may know him to be the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> he is call'd, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, That Lawleſs Prince that does what he will, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. 36. and the <hi>Son of Perdition;</hi> as <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> he is thus ſet out: To him <hi>was given a Mouth ſpeaking Great Things: He opened his Mouth in Blaſphemies againſt God, to blaſpheme his Name; The World wonder'd after him; They who dwell upon the Earth ſhall worſhip him; whoſe Names are not written in the Lamb's Book of Life; He comes, as Sathan, with All Deceivableneſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>urighteouſneſs in them, who periſh, on whom God ſends ſtrong Deluſion to believe ſo great a Lie, as the Papacy</hi> in its whole Frame, makes up. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare herein 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 10, &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 3. 8, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>City,</hi> that <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Great Whore, tbat corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Earth with her Fornications,</hi> Rev. 11. c. 17. That <hi>Woman Jezebel, which calleth her ſelf a Propheteſs,</hi> which <hi>Teacheth</hi> and <hi>Seduceth the People of Chriſt,</hi> Chriſtians by Profeſſion, to <hi>commit Fornication,</hi> to have Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with <hi>Idols,</hi> Rev. 2. 20. <hi>She hath on her Forehead a Name written, Myſtery,</hi> as if ſhe were indeed <hi>the Church of the Living God,</hi> the <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Truth, the Catholick Church,</hi> out of which none can be ſaved:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105101:13"/> But it is the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity;</hi> For the Inſcription goes on, <hi>Mother of Harlots;</hi> So that a moſt Unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible Compoſition of Wickedneſs makes up this <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Appeal now to All, whether ſuch Inſolencies of Arrogation ate to be found in the whole World, as in the <hi>Papacy</hi> and its <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> or whether ſuch Known Matter of Fact, in All theſe Things, could be more plainly ſet out, than they are by theſe <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charact.</hi> 5. The Great Fraud, Diſſimulation, World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Policy and Intrigue, we know in the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and the <hi>Pſeudo Catholick Roman Church,</hi> all its Cheats and Impoſtures make up ſuch a Character of it, that we find that Great <hi>Swediſh</hi> Stateſman, <hi>Puffendor,</hi> ſpends the whole Chapter forementioned in the Diſcourſe of it; who, the he does not appear to have the leaſt Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> yet writes ſo according to it on that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; That it is very wonderful; even as if he had aim'd to Juſtify <hi>Prophecy</hi> by ſo notorious matter of Fact.</p>
               <p>Let us then Review <hi>Prophecy</hi> on this Head, firſt in <hi>Daniel;</hi> The <hi>Little Horn had the Eyes of a Man;</hi> a <hi>Look,</hi> or Aſpect more Great, <hi>Rabbi-Like;</hi> of more Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicacity than his <hi>Fellow Horns; He had Eyes, and a Mouth that ſpoke Great Things;</hi> the <hi>Mouth,</hi> as of a <hi>Man of Eyes,</hi> Dan. 7. 20. <hi>He underſtood Dark Sentences; Through his Policy; He cauſes Craft to proſper in his Hand,</hi> c. 8. 25.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Revelation,</hi> c. 2. 14. In <hi>the Church</hi> of <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> the <hi>Prophetic</hi> Symbol of the Church of Chriſt Under the <hi>Antichriſtian Throne of Sathan,</hi> the <hi>Papal Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy;</hi> we read of that Politician <hi>Prophet—Balam,</hi> who taught <hi>Balac to caſt a Stumbling-block</hi> before the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105101:13"/> 
                  <hi>Children of Iſrael,</hi> by drawing them into Idolatrous Practices: In the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> the Symbol of the <hi>Proteſtant Churches,</hi> under <hi>Popiſh,</hi> Perſecuting Princes, ſtirred up by the <hi>Papal Antichriſtian (Church,</hi> as it will be call'd) which is Repreſented by <hi>Ahabs Queen Jeze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> then which none more apt in the whole <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> could be found, as might by a Compare be made apparent: But her <hi>Whoredoms</hi> and <hi>Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts</hi> cannot be paſſed by, with which <hi>Jehu</hi> upbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her ſo reproachfully, as the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes have done <hi>Rome:</hi> Oh that ſo many of them had not fallen into <hi>Jehu</hi>'s great Evil, not to have made a perfect <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> But That which is moſt to the preſent Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is, That ſhe had, together with her aſſumed <hi>Propheticneſs,</hi> the <hi>Depths of Sathan,</hi> as the <hi>Arcana Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> her deep Maxims of <hi>Sathanic</hi> State, by both which, ſhe enchants, be witches, intoxicates Princes and Nations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charact.</hi> 6. There is nothing more notorious, than the dreadful Perſecutions, and Storms of Violence, the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and <hi>Its Roman City,</hi> or Falſe Church hath raiſed againſt thoſe who have embraced Chriſtianity, and deſire to enjoy it in the Purity, and Simplicity of it; or have not ſubmitted to that Tyranny they have ſo graſp'd at, as hath been deſcribed. And we ſee the Princes and Powers of this World, that have been the Devotioniſts of it, have contributed their Force there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; The <hi>ſecular Authority,</hi> as <hi>they call</hi> it; and which <hi>Prophecy</hi> calls, <hi>The Ten Kings making War with the Lamb.</hi> And all this together hath come to that Extremity of Blood, Slaughter, and all manner of Torture, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to this very Day; Hiſtory and Experience are ſo full of it, I need ſay nothing. The <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> or as we call them, <hi>Vaudois,</hi> are a laſting Monument hereof, and continue ſo before our Eyes.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105101:14"/>
               <p> Now this Cruelty of Chriſtians (as they would be called) upon their own ſo honourable Name, is ſo monſtrous, that even <hi>Pagans</hi> cannot but be aſtoniſhed at it, and call into doubt that holy, harmleſs and compaſſionate Religion, ſo full of <hi>Mercy, Peace, all good Fruits,</hi> when they find the Profeſſors of it, and the <hi>Papacy</hi> and <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> who would be Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premes of it, <hi>breathing out Slaughter</hi> and <hi>Blood;</hi> to be as Lyons, Tygers, Wolves, yea Devils let looſe, <hi>ſet on Fire of Hell,</hi> upon thoſe who profeſs the ſame Lord and Chriſt; and ſuch Princes; as the <hi>French King</hi> to out-do the <hi>Neroes, Domitians, Decius's</hi> and <hi>Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians;</hi> and the <hi>Papal</hi> to equal, yea to exceed the Pagan <hi>Rome</hi> herein.</p>
               <p>And it ſhould make us bewail, that ever, what hath been call'd <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> ſhould have any of theſe Stains upon it, and abhor the leaſt Thoughts of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of any ſuch Thing in our own Nation.</p>
               <p>Let us now take a View of the Portraicture of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> and its Abundance, when it gives us the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of the <hi>little Horn;</hi> of the <hi>King of Fierce Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;</hi> of the <hi>lawleſs King,</hi> that <hi>does after his own Will;</hi> of the <hi>He,</hi> to whom <hi>Time, Times</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> are given; of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> all which are one and the ſame, <hi>Papacy of Rome,</hi> as hath been already, and may be now made out, even to the very Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Prophetic</hi> Explications; and as to the <hi>Pſeudo-Catholic Church of Rome:</hi> Dan. 7. 21. <hi>I beheld, and the ſame horn made war with the ſaints, and prevailed againſt them.</hi> Ver. 25. <hi>He ſpeaks great words againſt the moſt High, and ſhall wear out the ſaints of the moſt High.</hi> Chap. 8. 24. <hi>His power ſhall be mighty, but not by his own power, and he ſhall deſtroy wonderfully, and practiſe, and ſhall deſtroy the mighty and the holy people.</hi> Ver. 25.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105101:14"/> 
                  <hi>By Peace,</hi> as if he did nothing but in a Peaceable Way. Any thing of Force lies wholly on the <hi>ſecular Arm;</hi> He ſhall yet <hi>deſtroy many.</hi> In the <hi>Revelation,</hi> Chap. 11. 7. <hi>The Beaſt that aſcendeth out of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit ſhall make War againſt the Witneſſes of Chriſt, ſhall overcome them, and kill them.</hi> Chap. 13. 7. <hi>It was given,</hi> by Way of Permiſſion, but moſt judiciary Licenſe <hi>alſo to make war with the ſaints, and to overcome.</hi> Ver. 15. <hi>He cauſes, by his Supremacy in an Image, that all who would not worſhip the Image of the Beaſt ſhould be killed.</hi> Ver. 17. <hi>And that no man might buy nor ſell,</hi> have Freedom of Trade, (as it is now in <hi>France,) who would not receive the mark of the Beaſt, &amp;c.</hi> And till his Term expire, this muſt be; when it expires it ſhall end: There is therefore ſet up, as a Pillar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, as a Boundary of Time. Ver. 10. <hi>Here is the Faith and Patience of the Saints,</hi> Thus far it reaches, till the Time of Judgment on the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Horns:</hi> Then, <hi>He that leadeth, into Captivity ſhall go into Captivity; he that killeth with the Sword ſhall be killed with the Sword.</hi> Chap. 17. 14. <hi>The Ten Kings, Horns of the Beaſt, make war with the Lamb and his Saints.</hi> But the <hi>Beaſt is taken,</hi> and the <hi>Kings ſlain</hi> with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.</note> the Sword of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>City,</hi> or <hi>Papal Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> how abundant is <hi>Prophecy?</hi> Chap. 17. 6. <hi>I ſaw the woman drunken with the blood of the ſaints, and of the martyrs of Jeſus.</hi> Chap. 18. 6. <hi>Reward her as ſhe rewarded you.</hi> Ver. 20. <hi>Rejoice over her, Tbou Heaven, and ye Holy Prophets and Apoſtles, for God hath avenged you on her.</hi> Ver. 24. <hi>In her was found the blood of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and of the Martyrs, all that were ſlain on the Earth.</hi> Chap. 19. 2. <hi>God hath avenged the blood of his ſervants at her hand.</hi> And Chap. 11. 8. <hi>The</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105101:15"/> 
                  <hi>bodies of the witneſſes lay dead in the ſtreet of the great City;</hi> which by Compare muſt be <hi>Babylon the Great, the great City, ſpiritually called Sodom,</hi> for its <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> with her <hi>Fornication;</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> for her <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Tyranny;</hi> and with that as diſtinct a Remark, as could be ſet; <hi>Spiritually:</hi> All knowing their <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Uſurpation on that Word; The <hi>Spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> for the ſake of which, I could rejoice, if that very Word, in Uſe in our Nation, <hi>Lords Spiritual</hi> were utterly blotted out. Chap. 16. 3. The <hi>Angel</hi> that <hi>poured</hi> out his <hi>Vial</hi> on the <hi>Waters,</hi> and <hi>Rivers</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> its Papacy and Kings, ſaid, by way of Praiſe, <hi>Thou art righteous, Oh Lord, which art, waſt, and art to come; becauſe thou haſt thus judged, for they have ſhed the blood of thy Saints and Prophets, and thou haſt given them blood to drink, for they are worthy.</hi> And <hi>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther Angel from the Altar, where the ſouls ef Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs cry out, How long Lord!</hi> Anſwers; <hi>Even ſo, Lord God Almighty, True and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ighteous are thy Judgments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing then theſe Things of the Perſecutions of the <hi>Romiſh City</hi> in its whole <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Breadth,</hi> its <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> and <hi>ten Kings,</hi> are as clear as the Day; and that <hi>Prophecy</hi> is ſo direct upon them, if this very Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter were alone, it were even ſufficient to aſſure it is <hi>Papal Rome</hi> under the Eye of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> much more in this ſevenfold Concenterment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charact.</hi> 7. The <hi>Papacy</hi> is the laſt <hi>Supream</hi> of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and that <hi>Supremacy</hi> the very laſt State and Time of this <hi>City Rome.</hi> Now of this indeed we firſt ſay nothing beyond thoſe Scriptural Reaſons; That the final and moſt deſtructive Judgments of God are to be expected on a City of ſo great Idolatries, Filthineſſes, Pride, Cruelty and the bloody Perſecutions of the Servants of God, and of ſo long Continuances therein;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105101:15"/> as not only other <hi>Cities,</hi> who when they have <hi>fill'd</hi> up their <hi>Meaſures</hi> of Iniquity, have been <hi>judged</hi> by God; but <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which God made ſo great an Exemplar of Judgment; we may alſo obſerve in the Courſe of Providence, and the Government of the World, All humane States and Governments have come to their Periods; and <hi>Rome</hi> having had ſo long a Duration from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs Condita,</hi> or firſt Building of <hi>Rome,</hi> and even ſince it became <hi>Rome Papal,</hi> a Time as we may according to the moſt uſual Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of Time to Cities and States, the Sovereign <hi>Lord of Time</hi> hath determin'd, very well expect its Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall to be near, and that it muſt needs be ſitting on its laſt <hi>Supremacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when we calculate according to the <hi>ſure Word of Prophecy,</hi> as we have utmoſt Aſſurance, that <hi>Papal Rome</hi> is the <hi>Babylon,</hi> that is to be <hi>judged.</hi> So we have no Room for Doubt that it is the laſt <hi>Supremacy;</hi> For as the <hi>City</hi> is adjudged to final Deſtruction, ſo the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is thrice ſaid to <hi>go into Perdition.</hi> Chap. 18. 21, 22. compared with Chap. 17. ver. 8, 11. If therefore the <hi>City ſitting</hi> on the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> is <hi>caſt</hi> as a <hi>Milſtone</hi> into the <hi>Sea;</hi> That cannot ſurvive the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> to <hi>ſit</hi> on any other; And if the <hi>Beaſt go</hi> into <hi>Perdition,</hi> as he is alſo call'd by the Apoſtle, the <hi>Son of Perdition,</hi> [as the <hi>Judas</hi> of Chriſtianity, going into <hi>his own Place,]</hi> while the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſits</hi> upon him; there is a perfect End of his <hi>Supremacy</hi> alſo; he is therefore ſaid by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. to be firſt <hi>taken away</hi> by the <hi>Breath</hi> of the <hi>Lord's Mouth,</hi> and then <hi>brought utterly to nothing</hi> with the <hi>Brightneſs</hi> of his Illuſtrious Appearance, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 8. And he is <hi>taken,</hi> and <hi>caſt, alive, into the Lake;</hi> And even this gives certain Proof, This is the laſt <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy;</hi> For there can be none after the <hi>Eighth King,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:105101:16"/> upon which the <hi>City ſitting</hi> is deſtroyed: It could not therefore be the <hi>Seventh King,</hi> which by being called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Another,</hi> a very Forreigner, of another Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the other Kings, No Head of <hi>Babylon,</hi> though a King of <hi>Rome,</hi> is therefore certainly known to be the <hi>Chriſtian Emperor,</hi> and came after the <hi>Pagan Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror,</hi> call'd the <hi>Dragon,</hi> who then was in his Regnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, when the Apoſtle writ. Let us then argue thus; which ever of the Kings is the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> muſt be the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme; ſitting</hi> on which <hi>Babylon,</hi> (prov'd to be <hi>Rome)</hi> muſt be deſtroy'd: It cannot be the <hi>Sixth King</hi> who then was, when the <hi>Prophecy</hi> was given; and who might be ſuppoſed to have laſted til I now. For who can ſuppoſe in any Senſe whatever, <hi>Rome</hi> is upon the ſame <hi>King</hi> it was then! nor can it be upon the <hi>Seventh King,</hi> but no <hi>Head</hi> on that Account; for he could <hi>continue</hi> but a <hi>ſhort Space</hi> (as hath been elſewhere made out) it muſt be therefore ſome <hi>Supreme,</hi> that hath continued a long Space in Oppoſition to the <hi>ſhort Space.</hi> This therefore muſt be the <hi>Papacy</hi> which hath laſted longer than any Government over <hi>Rome</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Variation in any Eſſential Point, and than (ſo far as I know) any other in the World. Beſide, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid, the <hi>Dragon,</hi> by which I apprehend all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters underſtand the <hi>Pagan</hi> Imperial, perſecuting Power at the Time of the <hi>Revelation</hi> given, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid to receive a deadly Wound from the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperor;</hi> on which, he, as it were, ſecretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed over his Power, <hi>Seat,</hi> and <hi>great Authority to the Beaſt,</hi> gliding it, as unobſervedly, by the <hi>Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror,</hi> unto the <hi>Idolatrous Antichriſtian Papacy;</hi> by whom his <hi>Deadly Wound was healed;</hi> which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Eighth King,</hi> but <hi>Seventh Head; Seventh</hi> from the <hi>Sixth Head,</hi> or <hi>Pagan Emperor,</hi> of whom, when
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105101:16"/> the Apoſtle writ, it is ſaid, <hi>he now is.</hi> Then follows the Seventh King, no Head; then the Beaſt the Seventh Head who hath continued even above 1200 Years: So that the Time from the Ceſſation of the <hi>Weſtern Chriſtian Roman Empire,</hi> when the <hi>Beaſt received Power,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> with him at 476 of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Account, exceeds the Time from the firſt Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Rome</hi> to that Supremacy of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that no Title of Principality in <hi>Rome</hi> hath by a kind of Providential Fatality been aſſumed by any Secular Power, preciſely over the <hi>City Rome,</hi> but <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Pope of Rome;</hi> This argues beyond Poſſibility of Denial from this ſo long Continuance of the <hi>Papacy</hi> in Oppoſition to the ſhort Continuance of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth King,</hi> no <hi>Head,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian Emperor;</hi> that the Pope is indeed that <hi>Seventh Head,</hi> and <hi>Eighth King,</hi> and ſo the Laſt, even the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that <hi>goes into Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſit.</hi> 3. It is one of the Glories and Luſtres of the <hi>Judgment</hi> of God on <hi>Babylon,</hi> That the firſt coming of it into Execution ſhall be with great Suddenneſs and Surprizal. It is expreſſed <hi>in one Day,</hi> and <hi>one Hour,</hi> and in the <hi>ſame Hour.</hi> I know <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Hour</hi> may ſignifie any determinate Seaſon. But in ſuch very conſtant and pregnant Expreſſions of Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denneſs, exceeding Suddenneſs is intended. The ſame Expreſſions are uſed concerning <hi>Literal Babylon,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Eſay 47. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.</note> 
                  <hi>In one Day,</hi> and <hi>in a Moment, one Poſt ſhall run to meet another,</hi> with the Tydings, ſo ſudden and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought of Tydings; when <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> thought of no ſuch Thing; the <note n="†" place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Hand-writing appeared upon the Wall:</hi> And the <hi>ſame Night</hi> Belſhazzar <hi>was ſlain, and the King of the</hi> Medes <hi>took the Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian Monarchy</hi> then utterly ceaſing. This was <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105101:17"/> 
                  <hi>Typical</hi> of <hi>Myſtical Babylon:</hi> It is therefore no Argument this <hi>Judgment</hi> cannot be executed a long Time yet, becauſe there are no preſent Appearances: Herein ſhall appear the Glory of this <hi>Judgment,</hi> as one great Point of it, the Suddenneſs of it; In many of the moſt high and lofty Works of God, Suddenneſs hath been the peculiar Luſtre of them. In the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, <hi>He ſpake,</hi> and <hi>it was done; He</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 33. 9. Eſay</note> 
                  <hi>commanded,</hi> and <hi>it ſtood faſt;</hi> He <hi>called</hi> to the whole Creation, and <hi>it ſtood up together:</hi> In the Giving the <hi>Spirit, ſuddenly there was the Noiſe of a mighty ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Wind.</hi> In the Day of <hi>Judgment, ſudden Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> ſhall come, when <hi>they ſhall cry Peace, Peace;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 1.</note> upon all the Enemies of the Kingdom of Chriſt. <hi>The third Woe cometh quickly,</hi> in the haſty and ſudden Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 14.</note> of it.</p>
               <p>Now by this Suddenneſs it is not intended, That the whole Execution of the <hi>Judgment</hi> ſhould be in ſo ſhort Time, though it is and ſhall be in ſhort Time. For the whole Progreſs of the <hi>Third Woe</hi> is quick and ſpeedy as it paſſes through the <hi>Tubuli</hi> or Pipes, till it comes down into the Ocean of Everlaſting. Yet, it ſhall not be in one <hi>Day, Hour,</hi> or <hi>Moment:</hi> But the firſt Invaſion or Aſſault ſhall be ſo. Then it moves by <hi>ſeven Voices,</hi> and by <hi>ſeven Vials of the laſt Plagues,</hi> wherein is <hi>filled up</hi> the <hi>Wrath</hi> of Almighty God.</p>
               <p>To the Ancient <hi>Literal Babylon,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Eſay</hi> 47. 7. &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſayſt, I ſhall be a Lady for ever, ſo that thou didſt not lay theſe things to thy Heart, neither didſt thon remember the latter end of it; therefore hear now this, thou that art given to Pleaſures, that dwelleſt careleſly; thou that ſayeſt in thy Heart, I am, and none elſe beſides me; I ſhall not ſit as a Widow, neither ſhall</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105101:17"/> 
                  <hi>I know the loſs of Children: but theſe two things ſhal come upon thee in a Moment, in one Day; the Loſs of Children and Widowhood; they ſhall come upon thee in their Perfection, for the multitude of thy Sorceries, and for the great abundance of thy Enchantments.</hi> But then it is <hi>deſtroyed for ever, ſunk as a Milſtone.</hi> This ſpeaks the Perpetuity of the Judgment. All this is moſt <hi>Prophetically Typical</hi> of the <hi>Judgment</hi> on <hi>Myſtic Babylon.</hi> We have found it was literally fulfilled, as indeed in <hi>one Day,</hi> and <hi>one Night,</hi> on old <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſo it ſhall in the firſt Onſet on the <hi>Myſtical.</hi> But the Judgments of it are ſo much of another Nature, they ſhall continue much longer in the Execution, like the <hi>ſecond Death;</hi> it ſuddenly ſurprizes, but it continues for ever; ſo is the Judgment of <hi>Babylon;</hi> her Smoke riſes up <hi>for ever and ever.</hi> And, <hi>If any man worſhip</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. 9, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>the Beaſt or his Image,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the ſame ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God without mixture; and he ſhall be tormented with Fire and Brimſtone in the Preſence of God, and of the Lamb, and of the Holy Angels; and the Smoke of their Torments riſeth for ever and ever.</hi> Thus, though the Beginning of the Judgment be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, the Continuation of it is by certain Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of its ſelf, till it become an everlaſting <hi>Lake</hi> of <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Torment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſit.</hi> 4. The Princes that long bare up the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur and Haughtineſs of <hi>Papal Rome,</hi> by <hi>giving their Power and Kingdom to the Beaſt;</hi> called therefore, <hi>his Horns;</hi> ſhall be ſo <hi>overcome</hi> by the <hi>Lamb,</hi> as to be made Inſtruments in the Execution of the Judgment in ſuch Parts and Degrees, as the <hi>ſtrong Lord ſhall,</hi> when he becomes <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarch, King</hi> of <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords,</hi> commiſſion them unto. This ſhall highly exalt and make Illuſtrious the Judgment.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105101:18"/>
               <p> It is therefore much to be conſidered, and is a great Confirmation, that <hi>Babylon</hi> means <hi>Papal Rome,</hi> as hath been already at large ſet forth; that the ſo ſtrange and unaccountable Subjection of ſo many Kings to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> a feeble Power, if we conſider its Force of Arms, which <hi>Statiſts,</hi> and Men of <hi>Politicks</hi> have ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, is here accounted for; It is indeed call'd <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> and Intoxication, <hi>being made Drunk</hi> with the <hi>Wine of her Fornication,</hi> the moſt Lively Deſcription of Falſe Religion. But all is under the Divine Supreme Ordination;</p>
               <p>For God <hi>put it into their Hearts</hi> to <hi>Fulfil his will,</hi> and to <hi>agree together, and to give their Kingdom to the Beaſt,</hi> until the <hi>words</hi> of God ſhould be <hi>Fulfill'd;</hi> And they have <hi>one mind</hi> to <hi>give their Power</hi> and <hi>Strength unto the Beaſt;</hi> and hereupon they <hi>make War</hi> with the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and ſo Perſecute his Truth and Servants. And <note place="margin">C. 17. 2, 13, 15, 16.</note> the People of theſe <hi>Kingdoms, Nations, Multitudes, Tongues,</hi> the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the <hi>Roman Babilonian Earth,</hi> falling under the ſame Enchantment of a Falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>made Drunk</hi> and <hi>Commiting Fornication with her,</hi> are as a Confluence of <hi>Waters</hi> to her, on which ſhe <hi>ſitteth:</hi> Was there ever, or could there be a plainer Deſcription in <hi>Propheſy</hi> of what is ſo plain matter of Fact, which hath rais'd the Admiration and Wonder of all Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers!</p>
               <p>But when <hi>the words of God ſhall be Fulfilled,</hi> and the Time Allotted expired; Then theſe Kings ſhall ſo far as God pleaſes, be the Executioners of the <hi>Judgment;</hi> For as the <hi>Plagues</hi> in the Text are <hi>Death, Mourning, Famine, Burning with Fire;</hi> ſo the <hi>Kings</hi> ſhall <hi>hate the whore, make her deſolate, Eat her Fleſh, Burn her with Fire:</hi> It's True, there are <hi>Kings</hi> that <hi>Bewail her, v.</hi> 13. 18. But that pertains to another part of the Judgment,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105101:18"/> when it is Advanced to the <hi>Eternal Judgment,</hi> with the Explication of which I have not at the preſent to do; But how wonderfull and Illuſtrious will the Firſt Execution be, when theſe Kings ſhall Firſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in it! Sure It will be very Great and Glorious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Propos.</hi> 5. The Greatneſs and Sudden Invaſion of this Judgment, as Denounced by God, and by ſuch Inſtruments as the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> are uncontrolably to be Demonſtrated, not only as to the Poſſibility, but the certainty of both, as from the Truth of the Lord who hath ſo long ago Denounced it; So from the Wiſdom and Omnipotency of the ſtrong Lord, who is the Judger.</p>
               <p>This is not therefore in the leaſt unreaſonable, but the Higheſt Juſtification from the Trueſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Reaſon, is to be found in the Expectation of the Judgment upon the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and the <hi>City;</hi> Let it be never ſo ſudden. For the Lord is every way In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely <hi>Shrong,</hi> who <hi>Judgeth;</hi> God therefore in ſuch, his great works of what kind ſoever, appeals to the Conſideration of himſelf, as <hi>the God that ſtretcheth out the Earth,</hi> and <hi>that which cometh out of it, that giveth Breath</hi> unto the <hi>People</hi> upon it, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 42. So in the Judgment on <hi>Old Babylon: He that made the Earth by his Power, he hath Eſtabliſhed the World by his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and he hath ſtretched out the Heaven by his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; when he uttereth his Voice, there is a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Waters in the Heavens,</hi> and <hi>he Cauſeth the Waters to Aſcend from the Ends of the Earth; He maketh the Lightning with Rain,</hi> and <hi>bringeth the Wind out of his Treaſures.</hi> Jeremiah 51. 16. 17. It's therefore a very great Miſpriſion of Infinite Wiſdom and Power, when we make that an Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt Extraordinary, and moſt Miraculous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105101:19"/> Works of God, which he makes an Argument for Faith and Expectation of them, as if he were Tyed by what he had done, to do no more, or had done all he could do; and nothing to be Expected, but according to the Laws of Creation, and dayly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and Leiſurely Progreſſes, and not in thoſe Immediate Effects of Sudden Power; The great God argues differently, becauſe thoſe Works of his are ſo great and ſo high; That therefore ſtill ſo great and ſo high are to be Expected; and that they ſhould <hi>ſtand</hi> up ſo <hi>together,</hi> when he pleaſes.</p>
               <p>And ſo we unwiſely think, we very well argue, he that ſo Wonderfully and Miraculouſly appear'd in the Firſt Times of the Goſpel, hath done all that he will do, or thinks fit to be done, till the day of Judgment: But undoubtedly we may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter argue, he hath much greater things to do, to make the very latter times of the Goſpel-Glory, as Illuſtrious as their very beginning, and entrance was; Before his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Man of ſin</hi> and <hi>Son of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> ſhall be <hi>Conſum'd</hi> and utterly defaced; his <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall be poured out;</hi> The <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel</hi> ſhall be <hi>Preach'd;</hi> The <hi>Heathen</hi> ſhall <hi>come</hi> to the <hi>Lord</hi> from the <hi>Ends</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and ſhall <hi>know his hand</hi> and <hi>his might,</hi> and that his <hi>Name</hi> is <hi>Jehovah;</hi> And all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall <hi>Turn</hi> to the <hi>Lord</hi> and be <hi>ſaved.</hi> For <hi>Strong</hi> is <hi>the Lord,</hi> who ſhall do all theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſit.</hi> 6. The Divine Preſcience, and Wiſdom hath choſen and ſingled out a Time, and decreed it for the Execucion of this <hi>Judgment,</hi> when <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall ſhew it felf in it's Pride, in it's Pomp, it's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Security; For as, hath been ſaid, it is when ſhe ſhall ſay, <hi>I ſit a Queen,</hi> and ſhall <hi>ſee no ſorrow, as</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105101:19"/> 
                  <hi>Babylon</hi> of Old ſaid; I ſhall be <hi>a Lady for ever,</hi> and ſhall know <hi>no loſs of Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>Sudden Deſtruction,</hi> when Men cry, <hi>Peace, Peace.</hi> It is a Time when Men are High and Proud, and Haughty, that their Fall is near; <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> was laid hold on by Vengeance with thoſe <hi>words</hi> in his <hi>Mouth;</hi> Is not this <hi>Great Babylon,</hi> (from whence it had its Name in this <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. <hi>C.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Babylon the great;) The Great City,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>which I have built for the Honour of the Kingdom</hi> by the <hi>Might of my Power,</hi> and <hi>for the Honour of my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</hi> And while the <hi>word</hi> was in the <hi>Kings Mouth,</hi> the <hi>Judgment</hi> came upon him; So while <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> was in his Higheſt Jolity; <hi>Drinking Wine</hi> in <hi>Veſſels</hi> of the <hi>Temple;</hi> and <hi>Praiſing</hi> his <hi>Idols</hi> of <hi>Silver</hi> and of <hi>Gold;</hi> The <hi>Hand writing appear'd,</hi> and that <hi>Night</hi> he was <hi>ſlayn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it is certainly ſuch a Time to <hi>Romiſh Babylon</hi> at this very day. The <hi>Jubilee,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Centurial,</hi> is a Time, when ſhe <hi>ſits a Queen;</hi> is eſpouſed by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and is no <hi>Widdow,</hi> when her Children gather about her; the King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſo lately turn'd to her, and ſhe thinks ſhe can know no <hi>Loſs of Children;</hi> when ſhe ſits, as on a Throne, Diſpenſing Pardons and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, And a time it is, when ſo <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar-like</hi> a Prince is ſo Inſolently Vaunting, and ſo outragiouſly Perſecuting, and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes ſtand by, and are ſo Tender of the Articles of their late Peace, as not to be at Liberty to offer their Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Thus far I have ſetled the Great Poſitions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Judgment upon <hi>Babylon;</hi> To which I ſhall add to Corroborate what I have already laid down, and to make way to the Remaining Part
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105101:20"/> of the Diſcourſe, theſe following Obſervations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1. That together with the Judgment on <hi>Babylon,</hi> not when it begins; I would not be ſo miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; but when it comes to it's Perfection and filling up; There will be a concurrent Judgment upon the whole World of Wicked Men, the <hi>World of the ungodly;</hi> the <hi>Time of the Dead</hi> will then be <hi>come,</hi> that they ſhould be <hi>Judged:</hi> The <hi>Judgments of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 11. <hi>C.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>God will be made Manifeſt</hi> in <hi>all the Earth. Small</hi> and <hi>Great, Bond</hi> and <hi>Free,</hi> are <hi>ſlain with the Sword</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 19. 20, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>that proceedeth out of the Mouth</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>the word by which he Judgeth at the laſt Day;</hi> In the <hi>Burnings of Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Cities of the Nations fall;</hi> The Fire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins there and fpreads all over the Earth; Then will be the great <hi>Earthquake</hi> and Hail, <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lt.</hi> All theſe Expreſſions and many other are made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current, with <hi>Great Babylon coming up in Remembrance before God, to give</hi> her the <hi>Cup of his Fury;</hi> Now this ought to make greatly Remarquable to us the Judgment upon <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 2. The Judgment of God upon <hi>Babylon</hi> is Celebrated with his Higheſt Adorations, and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his Servants; Shewing at once the Higheſt Glory of God, and the Happineſs of his People in it: There were Loud Voices <hi>in Heaven,</hi> of <hi>Praiſe;</hi> and, the <hi>Four and Twenty Elders fell down on their Faces,</hi> ſaying, <hi>We Praiſe thee Oh Lord, who Art, who was, who Art to come; becauſe then haſt taken to thee thy Great Power,</hi> and <hi>haſt Reigned;</hi> Which is at <hi>Babylons</hi> being <hi>Judged:</hi> For then is the <hi>Allelujah of the Lord</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>God Omnipotent Reigning.</hi> Pſal. 149. Then is the Time <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C</hi> 19.</note> of the <hi>High Praiſes of God in the Mouths</hi> of his, of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105101:20"/> their <hi>Rejoycing in Glory;</hi> Then <hi>do they ſing the Song of Moſes</hi> the Servant of God and <hi>of the Lamb,</hi> as we find it at large; Then ſhall be the Four Courſes of <hi>Alle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 15. 3.</note> and all ariſing from <hi>Babylon, being Judg'd;</hi> that we have <hi>C.</hi> 19. 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And then is the Glory of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> State <hi>coming down,</hi> as a <hi>Bride A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned for the Bridegroom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then as the <hi>Eternal Judgment</hi> and the <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujahs</hi> of Eternal Glory, and Happineſs are two ſo great points of Scripture Truth; So by theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the <hi>Judgment of Babylon</hi> is declared a Great and a high point of Scripture Truth; Becauſe with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 21.</note> it are Complicated and Conſerved the Truths of the Goſpel, that have ſuch a Principality and Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in it; and they are ſo Interwoven with it, that the one cannot be Separated from the other; and the Judgment of <hi>Babylon</hi> ought therefore to be moſt cloſely attended to, and not looked upon as a dark <hi>Prophetical</hi> Truth, with which we have little to do; Let us then Humbly ſet our ſelves, as <hi>Daniel</hi> of old, to ſearch the Time in the <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> when this <hi>Babylon,</hi> as that of old, is to be <hi>Judg'd;</hi> and the whole Conſederacy of the Enemies of the Kingdom and Servants of Chriſt, yea all both <hi>ſmall</hi> and <hi>great</hi> Wicked; And then the Glory of Chriſt and his Reign ſhall appear; And let us haſt on to it with Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Prayer, Deſire and Expectation of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 3. It is moſt undeniable, The <hi>Prophecies</hi> of Scripture have continually given Numbers of Time, as when <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> are given into the <hi>Hand of</hi> the <hi>Little Horn,</hi> there is a Limitation of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> and Half; when the <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>daily Sacrifice</hi> was given for the taking it <hi>away,</hi> and the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 7.</note>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105101:21"/> 
                  <hi>Treading it under Foot;</hi> There is a Time aſſign'd from the very Firſt Date of the <hi>Viſion</hi> to the Time of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Juſtifying the Sanctuary,</hi> even 23000. <hi>Eves Morns,</hi> When the Queſtion was <hi>unto, how long the End of the Wonders;</hi> There is a Threefold Account of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> Time; <hi>Time, Times, Half a Time;</hi> 1290. <hi>Dayes</hi> and 1335 <hi>Days;</hi> In the <hi>Revel. C.</hi> 11. On the <hi>Gentiles</hi> coming into the <hi>Outer Court</hi> There are <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Two Moons</hi> Dererminate; and to the Counter <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> 1260 <hi>Days; Three Days,</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> lying <hi>Dead</hi> in the <hi>Street</hi> of the <hi>Great City;</hi> 1260 <hi>Days</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and Concurrent Three <hi>Times,</hi> and a <hi>Half; Forty</hi> two <hi>Moons</hi> of the <hi>Beaſts</hi> continuated Supremacy; And the <hi>Number of the Beaſt;</hi> 666 with a General Rule, and a Solemn <hi>Elogium</hi> of the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of <hi>Counting; Here is Wiſdom; Let him, that hath</hi> it <hi>Calculate,</hi> as the word properly ſignifies: And I ſay it is a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rule, There is the Same, or a Parity of Reaſon to Count throughout; And there are the ſame difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be overcome; For who indeed can once ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the Bleſſed <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth Leading</hi> into <hi>all Truth,</hi> the <hi>Spirit ſhewing Things to come,</hi> would have given in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> which we are Commanded to <hi>Search,</hi> and in the <hi>ſure word of the Prophecy;</hi> to which we are Commanded to <hi>give Heed</hi> as to a <hi>Light,</hi> that <hi>Shineth</hi> in a <hi>Dark Place;</hi> would have given theſe Numbers of Time, if he had not intended they ſhould be underſtood, and guided our Hopes and Prayers to the Time of his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 4. The Time of <hi>Babylon,</hi> or <hi>Rome Judged</hi> is the Time of the <hi>Papacy going</hi> into <hi>Perdition;</hi> The
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105101:21"/> Time of the <hi>Papacy going into Perdition</hi> is the Time of <hi>Rome Judg'd;</hi> For as the <hi>City</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> have been ſhewn to be Inſeparable; If the one be <hi>Roman,</hi> So muſt the other be alſo; ſo are they alſo, as to the Time of their being <hi>Judg'd:</hi> Herein they are Inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, when the one is Judg'd, So muſt the other alſo be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 5. That the Time of the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> and of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that <hi>carried</hi> her, muſt needs be very near, as will appear by that Account of Time, I ſhall now preſent upon ſuch <hi>Prophetical</hi> Grounds, as I hope, I cannot be miſtaken in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 6. Theſe Numbers all conſider'd, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuſted one to another, Reach down to <hi>Sixteen Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Ninety Seven</hi> of <hi>Vulgar</hi> account; and ſo as I have (in another Diſcourſe) even to Demonſtration made out; That from <hi>Solomons</hi> Death to the very Glory of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt; There lie in a due <hi>Series,</hi> and Connexion of theſe Numbers, 2730 Years, and in a moſt Exact Succeſſion of an 182 <hi>Indictions</hi> or Fifteens of Years; of which Eighty Four make the Juſt; <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time,</hi> ending at 97: This with many other Aſſurances, eſpecially of the coming to paſs of Events according to the <hi>Prophetic</hi> Figures, and the Times ſetled for them, ſo exactly agreeing, ſhew that Year, as the Year fixed for the Commencing from it of the happy Revolution of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt; I have in many Diſcourſes affirm'd this, and find no Reaſon to Retract it.</p>
               <p>That, which will, I know, with all Severity be objected againſt it, is, That things have not come to paſs according to Prediction and Expectation at that Year; And from thence will be inforced, That It is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105101:22"/> Preſumption to enquire into <hi>Prophetic</hi> Time, or to make any Determination upon it; I will therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſhew; It is not Preſumption, but a Duty to Enquire, what, or what manner of Time, The <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt in his Prophecys,</hi> hath <hi>ſignified;</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whatever, can be Agravated againſt miſtake: And that it is better to ſearch, notwithſtanding miſtake, then by Neglecting to ſearch, to think to be ſecure from miſtake; And then in the Second Place I ſhall apply my ſelf to ſhew, how the miſtake is from <hi>Prophecy</hi> to be explained and ſet Right, and yet <hi>Ninety Seven</hi> to be Vindicated, as the Great <hi>Prophetic</hi> Year.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, That it is not a Preſumption, nor Daring to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 49. 19. <hi>Jerem. C.</hi> 50, 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Appoint God a Time,</hi> or to ſtand, as a <hi>Shepherd,</hi> or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Time before him: But Duty to ſearch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture throughout, even to the <hi>Prophetical Numbers</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us therein. <hi>It is not for us</hi> indeed <hi>to know the Times</hi> and <hi>Seaſons,</hi> God <hi>hath ſet in his own Power;</hi> Yet to uſe all means, even by <hi>Books</hi> to <hi>underſtand,</hi> what ever God hath been pleaſed to give ſo far out of the Peculiar of his own Prerogative, as to <hi>Reveal,</hi> though in <hi>Myſtic Numbers;</hi> when he hath been pleaſed to <hi>Reveal,</hi> Things, They then <hi>belong</hi> to us: And <hi>Hee</hi> that hath a <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> hath an Obligation by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to <hi>Count;</hi> and our Lord charges it as Sinful <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Hipocriſy,</hi> not to ſearch, <hi>Diſcern</hi> thoſe either <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic</hi> or Moral <hi>Signs</hi> of the <hi>Times:</hi> And I cannot find what can be ſaid againſt the Commendation, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle gives to them, who <hi>give heed to the ſure word of Prophecy,</hi> as to a <hi>Light,</hi> that Shines <hi>in a Dark Place.</hi> Nor can I ſee;</p>
               <p>Why it ſhould be look'd on as an Offence, that is placed as a Character of Honour on the <hi>Sons of Iſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 32.</note> that <hi>they had underſtanding in the Times,</hi> which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105101:22"/> they attain'd undoubtedly by enquiry into and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation upon any <hi>Oracles,</hi> God had been pleas'd in thoſe <hi>Times</hi> to vouchſafe: <hi>Daniel</hi> thought it no Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to enquire further of the <hi>End of Wonders,</hi> when he <hi>underſtood</hi> not what was firſt Reveal'd; The <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 12.</note> account of the 1290, and of the 1335 Days to the very <hi>Bleſſed</hi> State was then given to him, not ſo much for himſelf, who was to <hi>go his</hi> way to Reſt until that End, but for us the People of God in every Age.</p>
               <p>What can then be objected againſt Searching in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Myſteriousneſs</hi> of thoſe <hi>Numbers?</hi> and what may be from the difficulty of Interpretation Argued? The very ſame may be objected againſt ſearching into any of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Scripture, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> calls them, or the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> Styles them, Things hard to be <hi>underſtood, Interpreted;</hi> and ſo we ſhould be Confined only to the moſt plain Scriptures, and of moſt Indiſputable Interpretation; whereas the Apoſtle Reſolv'd to <hi>Leave the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> as well ſecur'd; And to <hi>go on to Perfection</hi> in ſearch after the more Retyred Truths of the word of God, as concerning <hi>Melchiſedeec</hi> the Type of Chriſt, though <hi>hard</hi> to be <hi>Interpreted.</hi> Heb. 5. 11. 2 Pet. 3. 16.</p>
               <p>To the Objections Ariſing from the Danger, and miſcheif of miſtakes; It may be very well Anſwered by the due Conſideration; That in very many things without Error in the main Points, we <hi>Darken Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel by words without Knowledg;</hi> And if the miſtakes in <note place="margin">Job. 38. 2.</note> the moſt Eminent and Learned Servants of Chriſt, in Interpretation of Scripture and Explication of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra-Fundamental Points, moſt Inoffenſively to Subſtantiali Principles, were as Viſible, as miſtakes in Computation of <hi>Prophetic</hi> Time, we might, if miſtake were a Valuable Reaſon, be Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105101:23"/> from Reſearches, either into Scripture Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or the Truths of it, any further then in thoſe moſt undoubted Points, wherein all Holy Good Men agree.</p>
               <p>It is True, <hi>Prophetic</hi> miſtakes are, as I may ſay, ſurviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtill in the Eyes of Men; whereas the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of the other ſort, are, as they ſay of the Errors of <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> under <hi>Ground</hi> and out of Sight: Yet in themſelves no more; or Leſs Culpable; being uſeful for the ſhewing the Weakneſs and Fallibility of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Underſtanding, wherein it is not under the moſt certain Conducts of Truth.</p>
               <p>And as in other Caſes, Variety of Sentiments, and Enquiries ſhew the undoubted Excellency of Divine Truth; And Search into the word of God ſpeaks it the Greateſt Buſineſs and Exerciſe of Underſtanding; And is like the <hi>Running to and fro,</hi> whereby <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is Increaſed;</hi> whereas on the other hand a Kind <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 4.</note> of Reſolved ſullen Neglect, in General brings forth Ignorance, and Stupidity; and either a Superſtitious Dread of Intermeddling with Divine Things, if ſome what Removed from Common <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> or an Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Careleſſneſs; And in particular, In <hi>Prophetic</hi> Points of Time, this kind of Reſerving our ſelves from all the ſearch, we can make, is, as if God had given ſuch parts of his word to be only a <hi>Sealed Book;</hi> or the <hi>Cruces,</hi> the Torment of all ſearch and enquiry into them; or that we were Prophanely Careleſs, How Things are to be according to <hi>Prophecy</hi> with the Church of God, and with the Kingdom of Chriſt; or how the many and Great Predictions of Scripture, and of the Spirit of God by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> are to be Fullfill'd; But much Light, Knowledg, and awakenedneſs concerning them comes in by ſearch; and from hence alſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105101:23"/> proceeds Light, when we may humbly expect the Fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them, and thereby Faith, Hope, and Prayer be excited amongſt the Servants of Chriſt, ariſing from the Elaborate Treaties of thoſe, whoſe Hearts God hath engag'd to <hi>Separate themſelves</hi> to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with this Wiſdom,</hi> and Arm'd with Courage to bear the Reproaches of Men, upon their being miſtaken in openly Declaring and Publiſhing, what they have Found; And then this opens a way to <note place="margin">Paraeus. Napier. Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win. Moor, Jurieu.</note> further enquiries of themſelves, or thoſe, who may ariſe after them, for the ſetting Right in thoſe miſtakes. For ſo God hath been pleas'd by many Servants of his to make advances further and further, till the <hi>Day Dawn</hi> and the <hi>Day Starr Ariſe</hi> in the very <hi>Hearts</hi> of all his Servants.</p>
               <p>Nor can any one ſhew, why miſtakes in theſe <hi>Prophetical</hi> Enquiryes ſhould tend to <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> but quite the contrary; even as Different Apprehenſions upon Faithful and Diligent ſearching into other points do highly aſſure the main Foundation. Nor do I find miſtakes Springing from Faithful Endeavours, and ſincere Deſigns for the Truth, Glory, and <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> although Clouded with Infirmity, and our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but <hi>in Part,</hi> and <hi>Prophecying</hi> in <hi>Part,</hi> are through Grace in the Mediator Diſpleaſing to him, equally as Ignorance, Negligence, and <hi>Gallio-like,</hi> not caring for any of theſe things; The Evils of the preſent <hi>Sardian</hi> State, and even of the <hi>Angel</hi> or Miniſtry of it; That they do not ſearch with More United Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; That they might, as the <hi>Watchmen of Sion</hi> ſee <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſſay</hi> 52. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Eye to Eye,</hi> and <hi>lift up their</hi> Voices concerning theſe things.</p>
               <p>There is a Great Inſtance of a <hi>Prophetic</hi> miſtake, <note place="margin">2 Sam. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> and yet we find no Cenſure fix'd by the Spirit of God
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105101:24"/> upon it, where <hi>David</hi> Diſcours'd with <hi>Nathan</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet concerning <hi>Building God a Houſe;</hi> He ſpake as a <hi>Prophet; Go,</hi> and <hi>do all, that is in thy Heart; For the Lord is with thee,</hi> undoubtedly he underſtood by Scripture <hi>Oracles</hi> Gods choice of the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Judah</hi> and his Intention of Building a <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> like the moſt High and Loughty Buildings, and of that Firmneſs to be like the <hi>Earth Eſtbliſhed for ever:</hi> And therefore Collected; It was to be Built by <hi>David;</hi> Whereas, it is plain God had Determin'd, it ſhould be Built by <hi>Solomon</hi> the <hi>Son of David:</hi> He was Right <note place="margin">2 Sam <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> in the main, but Err'd in the Perſon, that was to be the Builder; But we find no ſevere Rebuke or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof; Only God is pleaſed to ſet him Right by his <hi>word</hi> coming to him that <hi>Night,</hi> and Inſtructing him concerning <hi>Solomon.</hi> I have humble hopes, that what may appear miſtake in the very Circumſtance of the Year 97, is Yet Right in the Eſſential Matter of a very near Time to be United with it; And, that what he hath been pleas'd to Enlighten me into in his word, ſhall ſet it Right; While I with great Humility and Modeſty, and not with too Great a Poſitiveneſs or Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Aſſurance, but Submiſſion to the Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the World, and Lord of Time, as to his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over all, ſo to his Wiſdom and Prudence in his Sure Word of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> Declare, what I find.</p>
               <p>For the Vindicating the Year 1697 to be the Great Year, where the Scripture <hi>Prophetic</hi> Line Centers for the End of the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half;</hi> of the 1260 Years of the <hi>Sack-Cloth,</hi> and the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> State; of the <hi>Fourty</hi> two <hi>Moones of</hi> the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and of the <hi>Beaſt:</hi> and yet that the great Effects of that Time did not appear I ſhall lay down this Poſition, as the Foundation of what is to Follow; The Great Effects to be Expected at the End of the Foremention'd Times <note place="margin">Poſition.</note> are to be by a Supreme Ordination of God, Transferr'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105101:24"/> from <hi>Ninety Seven,</hi> and are to be Humbly Expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the End of <hi>Three Years,</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> after the End of <hi>Ninety Seven, viz.</hi> at 1700.</p>
               <p>But in the firſt place, that I may clear the ſenſe of this Poſition; It muſt be conſider'd; That <hi>Prophecy</hi> doth not Reckon the Beginning and End of Years either according to the <hi>Sacred Iſraelitiſh</hi> Account, in the <hi>Vernal Equinox;</hi> or at our <hi>Vernal Equinox,</hi> which we call <hi>March 10th</hi> or 25. Nor at what we call <hi>January</hi> 1. But according to the Beginning of the <hi>Civil, Jewiſh,</hi> Year at the <hi>Autumnall Equinox:</hi> Of which we have an Unexceptionable proof; In, that The <hi>Sabbatizing Sacrifice</hi> and Oflering, by the offering <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 27.</note> once for all of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is Fixed in the <hi>Middle</hi> of the laſt of <hi>Daniel's Seventy Weeks,</hi> ſo U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally allowed to be <hi>Weeks</hi> of <hi>Years</hi> by All; The Time of which <hi>Offering</hi> muſt needs be (as All agree) at the <hi>Vernal Equinox;</hi> which was indeed made the Beginning of the <hi>Sacred Year,</hi> but not of the <hi>Civil Year;</hi> For then was the Time of the <hi>Jewiſh Paſſover:</hi> If then <hi>the Vernal Equinox</hi> was the <hi>Middle,</hi> or <hi>Half of the Week of Years,</hi> it muſt needs be the Half or Middle of the Fourth Year, whoſe Beginning and Ending can be no other than <hi>the Autumnal Equinox;</hi> to which Two Extreams <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Vernal</hi> is <hi>the Half,</hi> or <hi>Middle Point.</hi> And the Reaſon of <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſo accounting by the <hi>Civil Jewiſh Year,</hi> is very plain; For that it ſhould be ſome Account of Time, according to the Uſual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of the People of God, is moſt agreeable; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe To them were committed <hi>The Oracles of God;</hi> And ſeeing theſe <hi>Prophecies</hi> have Reſpect to the <hi>Monarchic Periods;</hi> Therefore that which concern'd the <hi>Sacred</hi> Conſtitutions was not ſo Congruous to <hi>Civil,</hi> and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to <hi>Pagan Dominions</hi> moſt intended: Let us
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105101:25"/> then account from the <hi>Autumnal Equinox</hi> 97, to the ſame 98, we have One Year; to the ſame 99, Two Years; to the ſame 1700, Three Years; and from thence to the <hi>Vernal Equinox</hi> of 1700, ending at 1701, according to the Computation of the Years ſo Begln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as we ſpeak in the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and we have the <hi>Three Years and a Half,</hi> at or before the End of which I have moſt Humble Hopes, through Grace, there ſhall be ſuch Aſſurance from the Great Effects, that we ſhall not doubt, the Year 1697, United with the Year 1700, is the very Time Prophecy hath ſet ſo Great Remarks upon, as the Time for the High Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and Revolutions, God will pleaſe to make in the World.</p>
               <p>Now if the Lord pleaſe, upon the Foundation of theſe Propoſitions, to Direct his moſt Unworthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that hath Reaſon to be Humbled and Abaſed, in Regard of the Failure of the Great Expectation at 1697. and yet to ſhew him, how the Great, and Compleat Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects then Expected, and that That Year made ſome Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertures of Themſelves, may be Transferr'd to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Year of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> 1700, as a Year ſo Remarkable by the Providential Ordination of the <hi>Jubilee</hi> upon it; a Time to which Prophecy ſo Points; without any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to 97, or Injury to <hi>Prophecy.</hi> And that I may, without Juſt Imputation of Preſumption, Humbly Preſent that Fair Collineation of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> together with the Plain, Undeniable Encouragement of the Text, I am upon, to ſtir up the Earneſt Prayers, and Humble Waitings of All his Servants, <hi>Loving and Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his Kingdom;</hi> to ſee what God will pleaſe to do this Year; Oh how Great will his Goodneſs be herein! and beyond this I will not dare. And if the Lord be pleaſed to Honour this Enquiry with his Great Works,</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:105101:25"/>
               <p> I will therefore propoſe theſe Six Heads to inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in order to ſo Great Ends.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I will conſider what is to be ſaid concerning <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Seven,</hi> with Relation to the Great Events I have aſſign'd to it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I will ſhew, that there are Reſerves in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> in ſome Caſes, within it ſelf, of ſome further Time, that ſhall lye within the moſt Known, Noted and Expected Time; and though it Reach out beyond it, it is yet United, as One Time with it; and ſo it will be found in the Times now before us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This ſhall be Endeavour'd to be made out, That in ſuch a Caſe there may be found in <hi>Prophecy</hi> a Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Artifice, or Contrivance of the Divine Spirit of it, that there ſhall be an Equipoize of it, that may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Injury to it, be inclin'd the one way, or the other, by the Hand of Interpretation: And though that Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit, the Author of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> moſt Certainly Fore knew to which it would be by Providence De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd; yet without Immediate Revelation from Himſelf, no Humane Underſtanding could Determine. All which ſhall be particularly ſhewn in this Inſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 97 and 1700.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I ſhall obſerve with Scripture-Authority, That when there is a Delay of Events, and Effects of Mercy, beyond the Principal Time, moſt Openly held out in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> it is call'd <hi>Infraction,</hi> or <hi>Breach of Promiſe:</hi> And when Providence Retracts what it had Begun, and given ſome Eſſays of, It is call'd <hi>Abruption,</hi> or <hi>Breaking off</hi> what was ſo Begun; And That, Sin is the Demerito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Cauſe in Both Theſe Caſes, and herein alſo a particular Application to the preſent Caſe ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:105101:26"/> 5. That the Certain Determination of a Time Acceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and in Delay of the Principal Time, is in neither made doubtful, or Incertain; but it carries the more Forcible Aſſurances from the Delay, upon that further Time. And this is alſo Reduced to the preſent Caſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That the Cloſeſt Enquiries into theſe Things, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God, is on no True Account of the Matter, a Blame-worthy Preſumption, but encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd by Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Head</hi> 1<hi>ſt.</hi> With Relation to <hi>Ninety Seven</hi> Paſt, I muſt take the Humble Boldneſs to ſay, I have made a Review upon my whole <hi>Prophetic Scheme,</hi> Backward and Forward; and conſidered the mutual Reſpects to, and Configurations of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> one with another; and their Juſt Spaces of Time; and could find nothing that ſhould ſhake my Aſſurance, but had it much more Confirm'd by that <hi>Plerophory,</hi> or Full Aſſurance of Underſtanding; ariſing from the whole <hi>Prophetic</hi> Line, being from <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Death compacted under that <hi>Chronologic</hi> Period of <hi>Indictions,</hi> or <hi>Fifteens of Years,</hi> (as I have moſt Fully in a Diſcourſe on that Subject, made to appear), even to the End of the 1335 <hi>Days,</hi> or the Bleſſed Time: So that I cannot remove from <hi>Ninety Seven,</hi> as that <hi>Central</hi> part of Time in the <hi>Prophetic Line,</hi> without diſtruſting the Truth of Human Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and even <hi>Arithmetic Demonſtration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But being very well Aware of this Great Preſſure upon me, That ſeeing the great Effects I expected at that Time, did not appear; It muſt neceſſarily be inferr'd; That either the word of Prophecy, (which is to be abhorr'd) is not ſure; Or that <hi>Ninety Seven</hi> is not the Time, <hi>Prophecy</hi> hath Directed us upon; For it cannot be the Time, if it be not Illuſtrious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105101:26"/> with thoſe mighty Events, as the Great Effects of <hi>Viſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On this therefore I moſt Humbly beſought the Lord, that he would clear this Difficulty to me; concerning which I cannot but have Greateſt <hi>Searchings</hi> of <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Thoughts of Heart;</hi> And it hath pleas'd Him, and doth ſtill pleaſe him to Impreſs much on my Thoughts; That the <hi>Three Days</hi> and <hi>a Half</hi> Aſſign'd to the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Lying Dead</hi> in the <hi>Streets</hi> of the <hi>Great City,</hi> Should according to the <hi>Prophetic</hi> Standard be, as <hi>Three Years</hi> and <hi>a Half</hi> laid to <hi>Ninety Seven;</hi> And then ſhall thoſe <hi>Mighty Works</hi> expected <hi>ſhew forth</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>But that this may not appear Fancyful or <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtic,</hi> I am obliged to turn my ſelf every way to <hi>the Law</hi> and <hi>to the Teſtimony;</hi> As the <hi>Prophets Searched</hi> (no doubt) throughout the Sacred Records to find; <hi>What,</hi> or <hi>what manner of Time,</hi> The <hi>Spirit of Chriſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>which was in them, did ſignify;</hi> So that I may find, How theſe <hi>Three Days</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> may be ſo added to 97, as to be Conſonant, and Agreeable with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and <hi>Prophetic</hi> Meaſures; and particularly how it may be Reconcil'd with what I have Found, and can yet find no Reaſon to Retract, concerning 97.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Head.</hi> 2. I will come therefore to ſhew; That there are Reſerves of <hi>Prophecy</hi> in ſome Caſes within itſelf; and that it ſets a further Time, when it hath Firſt ſet any Time more open, and in view; and that further Time Reaches out beyond it; It is yet but as one Time United with it; And ſo it will be found in the Time now before us. Concerning two ſuch Times United, as into one; I would ſet in full, and open view to Run on every occaſion into Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105101:27"/> theſe Rules to Judg of them by, which have been already Intimated.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Principal Time is held out more clearly and openly; The other by way of Reſerve is given; as a <hi>Mantiſſa</hi> or Surpluſage, or as an <hi>Epitome</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection of that Time; and cannot be found but by cloſeſt Attention to what hath been before Revealed; Or by New Revelation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When ſuch a Reſerved Time is, the Principal, Primary, Determined Time is not Removed from its Dignity. But it is alway Decorated, or Graced with offertures of ſome very Great Events, And though the further Reſerved Time is made moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious with the whole Conſtellation of Events, yet that Surpluſage or Conſummation of Time Reſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Principal, as its Baſis and Foundation both for Time, and alſo for thoſe Great Events. <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. When ſuch a Reſerved Time is, it is Generally a very ſhort Time, with Relation to the Time that went before that Principal Time, and was to End in it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When this Reſerved Time is Expired, God is pleas'd ſo to order; It ſhall never be Tranſcended or Exceeded, but the whole of Events deſigned ſhall be Compleated at it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This lengthning out Principal Time by ſuch a Reſerve, or <hi>Mantiſſa</hi> of Time, it is either in a way of Wiſdom and Goodneſs for Gracious Reaſons towards his Churches; Or it is in Juſtice and Diſpleaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the undue, and unſuitable Frame and State of his People to ſuch Mercies, as that Time deſigned ſhould have brought forth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When it is in a way of Diſpleaſure, It is Expreſs'd by a word, that Imports Infraction, or Violation, or as in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105101:27"/> our Tranſlation, <hi>My (i. e.</hi> Gods) <hi>Breach of promiſe, Numb.</hi> 14. 34. The ſame word ſignifies <hi>Abruption</hi> or breaking off the even Contexture of Events begun; All which have been mentioned already.</p>
               <p>I will now, according to theſe Rules, diſcourſe this Head. But that I may do it with Greater Clearneſs, I find it moſt advantageous to ſhew, that in the Two Laſt Rules, the various Inſtances of Reſerved Times in Scripture, are Depoſited, <hi>viz.</hi> Reſerves of Time in a way of Goodneſs, and Mercy; and in a way of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and <hi>Breach of Promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe Two Reſervings of Time, being the only Kinds, <hi>viz.</hi> Mercy, or Diſpleaſure;</p>
               <p>I will firſt give an Inſtance of God's Diſpenſations in a way of Goodneſs, Grace and Mercy, in ſuch a Reſerve of Time.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> was that very <hi>Fullneſs of Time,</hi> that very <hi>To Day</hi> of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4.</note> made Known the <hi>only Begotten Son,</hi> and for <hi>our Lords Entring into his Glory.</hi> All Power in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.</note> was <hi>Given to Him,</hi> for his Spiritual Kingdom, which He then Receiv'd, and for <hi>the pouring out of his Spirit;</hi> Then he Received the <hi>Sealed Book</hi> of all diſpoſes over the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of <hi>this World.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And yet there were <hi>Fourty Days</hi> Surpluſage of Time from the Reſurrection of Chriſt to his Aſcenſion; And Fifty Days from his Death to the <hi>giving the Spirit:</hi> Now the Death of Chriſt was plainly Foretold in the <hi>Middle</hi> of the <hi>Laſt Week;</hi> And then he could not be <hi>Holden of Death,</hi> but muſt <hi>Riſe again</hi> the <hi>Third Day according to the Scriptures:</hi> But that he ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue with his Diſciples ſo long, and that from his Death <hi>Fifty Days</hi> ſhould be made up to the <hi>Giving of the Spirit</hi> was not ſo plainly Revealed. Indeed if we
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105101:28"/> could have laid our thoughts before, or now cloſely, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Diſtance of Time between the two <hi>Feaſts</hi> of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> and <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> or the <hi>Feaſt</hi> of <hi>Weeks;</hi> and that the Antitype muſt Anſwer the Type; we might find ſome Ombrage of it; But it was ſo obſcure, as hardly to be Traced till Reveal'd in the Hiſtory of the Event, though, ſo prefigur'd at ſuch a D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtance. Now this was in Mercy; That our Lord Chriſt might give thoſe <hi>many,</hi> and <hi>Infallible Proofs</hi> of his Reſurrection, and <hi>ſpeak</hi> to his Apoſtles, <hi>whom he had choſen,</hi> of the <hi>Things pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Kingdom of God.</hi> But the <hi>Effect of Viſion</hi> was herein much Lower, then in his <hi>ſitting down on the Right Hand of the Majeſty on high</hi> in the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and his <hi>making Interceſſion for us.</hi> So the moſt Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Effects were not till ſuch a Time after, yet ſtill the Principal Time was not Remov'd from its Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; For the Death and Reſurrection in that moſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Period of Time, <hi>the Half Week,</hi> Remains the very <hi>Baſe</hi> of the <hi>Forty Days;</hi> and to all After-Time, the very Hinge on which it turns, till it ſhall come to the <hi>Fullneſs of All Times,</hi> the Kingdom of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 10. And as this was but ſuch a ſhort Time, ſo it did but ſumm up, and Recollect the Glorious Miniſtry of our Lord Jeſus, and could not be exceeded.</p>
               <p>In the way of Judgment, I give a Second Inſtance; The <hi>very ſelf ſame Night</hi> of the 430 Years, Incluſive, of the 400 Years aſſign'd to <hi>Abraham, Gen:</hi> 15. had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Great Event of the <hi>Going out of Egypt;</hi> yet that Glorious Conſtellation of Events, Bringing into <hi>the Land of Promiſe,</hi> and <hi>Caſting out the Nations,</hi> was not perform'd till <hi>Forty Years after.</hi> This was indeed no way, that we Know now, to have been found, but by God's ſo Immediate Revelation of <hi>Forty Days Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically given,</hi> a <hi>Day for a Year:</hi> It was but a ſhort
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105101:28"/> Time, compar'd with the 430 Years; And it could not be Tranſcended: The Certainty of the Higheſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of the <hi>Great Promiſe</hi> Fullfill'd, was there to Begin: And <hi>the Forty Days of Years</hi> was but a <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſage of Time,</hi> and a <hi>Recollection, and Summing up of the Sojourning State</hi> of the 430 Years.</p>
               <p>But that which I have eſpecially to Remark upon it, is, That it was in the way of <hi>Infraction of Promiſe,</hi> and <hi>Abruption of that Contexture,</hi> or <hi>God's Breaking off</hi> from what he had begun to do in the <hi>Deliverance out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> ſignified by that <hi>Hebrew</hi> Word, ſo Emphatic hereof, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14. 34, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>But yet this very End of the 430 Years Remain'd the Foundation of the Time following after, and was not mov'd from its Dignity; For the <hi>paſſing through the Red Sea,</hi> and <hi>Pharoah's</hi> Overthrow in it, the Victory over <hi>Amal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k;</hi> the <hi>Nomotheſia,</hi> or the <hi>Giving of the Law,</hi> the <hi>Rearing of the Tabernacle,</hi> Reſted All on this Time, and its Great Event; and <hi>the Forty Years</hi> are dated from it; which were elſe but <hi>Thirty Eight Years</hi> from the <hi>Ill Report</hi> of the <hi>Spies,</hi> to the Entry upon <hi>Canan;</hi> and the Ending of the Following Courſe of Time, to <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s ſo Reſplendent Reign; and <hi>the Building of the Temple is Dated</hi> from it; 480 Years, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 1. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from <hi>the Going out of Egypt.</hi> And this Inſtance is the more Remarkable; Becauſe although this Time was Known to, and Reſolved of God as <hi>before, as all his Works,</hi> from <hi>the Foundation of the World;</hi> Yet it comes in by way of <hi>Infraction of Promiſe;</hi> and it broke off the Contexture of Great Deliverances: It is Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſo in Prophetic Language therefore, a <hi>Day for a Year,</hi> as in our <hi>preſent Prophecy,</hi> we are upon, and was upon the Account of <hi>Provocation,</hi> and unſuitable Frame to <hi>Deliverances;</hi> and the End of this Surpluſage of Time
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105101:29"/> touches the <hi>Entring into the Land of Promiſe,</hi> the <hi>Type of the Glorious Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another</hi> Inſtance of this Kind may be; <hi>The Seventy Years of the Babyloniſh Captivity</hi> had their moſt Known and Celebrated Period in <hi>the Firſt Year of Cyrus,</hi> as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarch</hi> in <hi>the Second of the Four Kingdoms,</hi> the <hi>Perſian Kingdom;</hi> we find therefore his Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Twice Recorded in Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> in the End of <hi>the Second Book</hi> of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> and in <hi>the Beginning</hi> of the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Ezra:</hi> But here was not the Complement of Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; The <hi>Spirit of God</hi> Gives Account of ſeveral ſtops and ſtays, till <hi>the very Seventh</hi> Year of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> There the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Reſtoring Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had its full <hi>going forth;</hi> It was all yet, as one United Time of the <hi>Words going forth to Reſtore</hi> and to <hi>Build Jeruſalem.</hi> It began in the <hi>Decree,</hi> Firſt of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> then of <hi>Darius,</hi> then of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> King of <hi>Perſia. Ezr.</hi> 6. 14. which ſo full decree of <hi>Artaxer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes</hi> we have <hi>C.</hi> 7. 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This he makes as Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to <hi>Cyrus</hi> in that <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and of which <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> was the <hi>Golden Head; viz.</hi> of the <hi>Four <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Kingdoms;</hi> and ſo ſtyles himſelf <hi>King of Kings;</hi> Now here Great <hi>Abruption</hi> had been from what God begun in <hi>Cyrus.</hi> So that the work was ſtayed to the <hi>Second Year</hi> of <hi>Darius. Ezr. 6th</hi> 24. Then another <hi>Seventy Years</hi> had ſlid in, Recorded by <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah. C.</hi> 1. 12. Which had their <hi>Epoch</hi> or beginning as may be Computed from <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> 23<hi>d</hi> Year. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 50. 30. At the laſt <hi>Captivation.</hi> And here the <hi>Provocation</hi> was, as may be Collected from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writers at that Time; the unwillingneſs of the <hi>Jews</hi> to Leave their <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Plantations; And thoſe who did go up to <hi>Judah,</hi> neglected the <hi>Houſe of God</hi> to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Zech.</hi> 2. 6.</note> Build their own <hi>Ceiled Houſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105101:29"/>
               <p> The Great Delay of the Glorious Kingdom of Chriſt due to him at his Reſurrection, is ſo Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendental to all other Caſes; and for which delay <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and <hi>Prophecy</hi> was ſealed at his Death, until the very Time we are now waiting for; I do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to Inſiſt upon at this Time; being ſo ordain'd by the Father, and by the Mediator for Holy and Wiſeſt Reaſons too large for the preſent.</p>
               <p>Now in theſe Reſerved Times they are ſo given in <hi>Prophecy;</hi> That they might wholly have United with the Principal Times beginning and ending toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but when they by the Event Run out beyond ſuch Principal Times, It then appears they were ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd by <hi>Prophecy</hi> to do. And when they are in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; They ſeem, as it were to Uſurp upon the Time immediately following Thoſe Principal Times; As the <hi>Forty Years</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> Invaded ſo much Time of enjoying <hi>Canaan</hi> before the <hi>Reigns</hi> of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> Abridging and cutting it 40 Years ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: In The ſtay of the <hi>Building,</hi> and <hi>Reſtoring</hi> the <hi>Houſe of God</hi> from <hi>Cyrus</hi> to <hi>Darius,</hi> and the full Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration not made till <hi>Artaxerxes</hi>'s Seventh Year, The following Time of enjoying that <hi>Reſtored</hi> State was ſo much Decurtated, Abbreviated, and Retrench'd.</p>
               <p>When ſuch a Delay is in Mercy, as in our Lords ſtay upon the Earth beyond his <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> The Time following the Principal Time, as the <hi>Fourty Days</hi> of Chriſt with <hi>His,</hi> is Enrich'd with Great Appearances of the <hi>Bridegroom</hi> not <hi>taken from</hi> the <hi>Children of the Bride Chamber;</hi> And yet it was a Delay of Chriſts Appearance in Heaven, and of the Spirit poured out.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:105101:30"/>
               <p> I look upon theſe Inſtances as full Proof, That there are ſuch <hi>Mantiſſa</hi>'s, or <hi>Surpluſages,</hi> ſuch Recollections, or <hi>Epitomes</hi> of <hi>Reſerved Time,</hi> beyond the moſt Noted and Principal Times, before which the high Events may not be Compleated, but then moſt certainly ſhall; I ſhall now in the following Heads apply my ſelf to <hi>Ninety Seven;</hi> whoſe Great Events have not yet been fill'd up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Head.</hi> 3<hi>d.</hi> I come therefore to the Third Head; And moſt particularly to ſhew the Curious Artifice, and Contrivance of the Divine Spirit in the ſo giving the <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> in the 1260 <hi>Days;</hi> That there may be a Reſerved Time, and under ſuch an Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poize of Interpretation; that the Reſerved Time may be drawn up into, and within the Principal Time; Or may be extended beyond it into ſome further Time, and no Determination, but by the Providential E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
               <p>The Time, that may be Reſerv'd, and Extended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> I have already aſſign'd to be the <hi>Three Days</hi> of Years and a <hi>Half;</hi> The end of which ſhall have the whole Conſtellation of Events, Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd from the End, or Period of the 1260 Days up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelf; <hi>viz.</hi> from 1697 to 1700, As on purpoſe to Fulfil; I truſt; the word of the Lord; That what Time <hi>Babylon</hi> ſaith, <hi>I ſit a Queen,</hi> her <hi>Plagues</hi> ſhould begin to come in <hi>one Day.</hi> And herein I cannot but hope, The Beauty and <hi>Symmetry</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſhall be ſeen between 97, as the Principal Time; and the <hi>Three Years and a Half</hi> as the Recollectionary Time ending with the <hi>Jubilee</hi> 1700; To this very great purpoſe I lay down the following <hi>Scheme</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> concerning this Point, as in its Equipoize between 97, and 1700.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:105101:30"/> 1. The firſt thing I obſerve herein is; That after the <hi>Great High Preiſt,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtle of our Profeſſion;</hi> The Man <hi>Cloathed in Linnen,</hi> had given in Anſwer to the <hi>Angels,</hi> who asked, <hi>How Long to the End of theſe Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 5. &amp;c.</note> That there ſhould be a Delay of <hi>Finiſhing</hi> for <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Times,</hi> and a <hi>Half.</hi> He alſo added; when <hi>He (i. e. the Scatterer) ſhall have accompliſhed to ſcatter the Power of the Holy People; All Theſe</hi> (viz. <hi>Wonders) ſhall be Finiſh'd. Daniel</hi> complains, <hi>He heard, but he underſtood not.</hi> Now it is true, <hi>the Prophets</hi> did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Particularities of All that was <hi>Reveal'd</hi> to them concerning <hi>Time;</hi> but were left to <hi>ſearch, what,</hi> or <hi>what manner of Time, the Spirit of Chriſt, which was</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>in them, did ſignifie:</hi> Yet even their Doubts, Recorded in Scripture, were under <hi>Divine Inſpiration,</hi> and are ſo order'd, as to give Occaſion to Further Revelation; But <hi>Time, Times, and Half,</hi> were Reveal'd to <hi>Daniel</hi> before, to be <hi>given to the Little Horn, to wear out the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Saints of the Moſt High,</hi> which was the ſame thing with <hi>ſcattering the Hand of the Holy People:</hi> That then needed not a <hi>New Repetition:</hi> The Thing therefore he underſtood not, was, <hi>What Time the Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſcatter</hi> might take up.</p>
               <p>He Appeals therefore to <hi>his Lord,</hi> and <hi>our Lord; My Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what ſhall the End of Theſe (i. e.) Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders be?</hi> His Queſtion is directed upon the very Point <hi>he underſtood not;</hi> and Receives Anſwer in <hi>Three Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That there will be a Cloſedneſs, and a Seal of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy, ſet upon the Determinate <hi>Time of Wonders Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing,</hi> viz. till the Event determines it; The <hi>Seal on the Foreheads of the Servants of God,</hi> Remains till the End; and till the End, or very <hi>Accompliſhing to ſcatter,</hi> They cannot be diſtinctly known; For till then the <hi>Witneſſes</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105101:31"/> appear not <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeal'd,</hi> or with the <hi>Father's Name writ on their Foreheads, in a Riſen State,</hi> on <hi>Mount Zion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is Given as a <hi>Diagnoſtic,</hi> or diſtinct Note of the <hi>Time between the End</hi> of <hi>the Times and Half,</hi> or the 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> and the <hi>Time of Accompliſhing to ſcatter; Many ſhall be Purified, and made White, and Tryed;</hi> which we may very well underſtand of thoſe they call, <hi>The New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts,</hi> or the <hi>Re-united;</hi> who have ſince been made <hi>White by Repentance,</hi> and Purifying Grace; who have been <hi>made Wiſe,</hi> by Remembring what they had <hi>Receiv'd,</hi> and <hi>Heard of the Goſpel-Purity,</hi> and Return'd to it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a new out of <hi>Babylon;</hi> while Perſecutors will not underſtand, but <hi>do more and more wickedly, Perſecuting</hi> and <hi>Scattering,</hi> till the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tmoſt End and Accompliſhment of Scattering.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Great <hi>Palmoni,</hi> or <hi>Wonderful Numberer of Time,</hi> inſenſibly, and yet as in Anſwer to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, gives a further Delineation of <hi>Time</hi> in <hi>Thirty Days,</hi> added to the 1260, making them 1290; under an <hi>Epoch,</hi> or Beginning, Characteriz'd with the <hi>Taking away the Daily,</hi> viz. <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> and the <hi>Abomination,</hi> that <hi>maketh Deſolate, ſet up;</hi> which I look upon, moſt Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, to be argued to be <hi>the Antichriſtian Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy,</hi> by <hi>the Papal Gentiles</hi> Entring into the <hi>Outer Court,</hi> and ſo <hi>Taking away the Truly Chriſtian Worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to theſe <hi>Thirty</hi> of the 1260, are added <hi>Forty Five,</hi> making the 1290 1335. Reaching to <hi>the very Bleſſed State</hi> of <hi>the New Jeruſalem,</hi> in which <hi>Daniel</hi> is aſſured a <hi>Lot:</hi> and, in the mean time to reſt his Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enquiries, and Himſelf to <hi>Reſt</hi> in Spirit with Chriſt; and his Body in the Grave.</p>
               <p>Now then ſeeing theſe <hi>Thirty</hi> are added to the <hi>Times and Half,</hi> which <hi>the Spirit of Prophecy</hi> hath Expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into 1260 <hi>Days of Years;</hi> And that there can be no
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105101:31"/> 
                  <hi>Time</hi> between the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half,</hi> and <hi>Finiſhing,</hi> by the Expreſs Word; except the ſpace of <hi>Accompliſhing to Scatter;</hi> and that the ſame <hi>Spirit of Prophecy</hi> hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven no other, ſo much as ſuppoſeable ſpace, but the <hi>Three Days of Years, and a Half;</hi> Either thoſe <hi>Three Days and a Half</hi> muſt be ſuppoſed to Unite with the <hi>Three Times and Half,</hi> and to be One with them; or they muſt Extend themſelves upon the <hi>Thirty,</hi> and be the Firſt <hi>Three Days of Years and a Half</hi> of them; For they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye between them, as a part of Neither: If ſo, either the 1260 muſt be 1263, and a <hi>Half;</hi> or the 1290 muſt be 1293 and a <hi>Half;</hi> Either of which is very contrary to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> which is moſt expreſs in each; <hi>viz. Times and Half,</hi> or 1260 <hi>Days;</hi> and 1260, with <hi>Thirty</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, 1290 <hi>Days,</hi> and no more of Either. Now here is the <hi>Equipoize of Prophecy:</hi> It could not be Determined before the Event, whether the Accompliſhing to <hi>Scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> might Unite with <hi>Time Times, Half Time,</hi> as the laſt <hi>ſcattering;</hi> Or go further within the 30. But the Event hath Determined, The <hi>Three Years</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> Extend upon the Firſt <hi>Three Years</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> of the <hi>Thirty,</hi> making 1260 1290. And the Curious Artifice of <hi>Prophecy</hi> is herein ſeen; For thus the 1260 and 1290 are joyn'd in the <hi>Taking</hi> away the <hi>Dayly</hi> by thoſe <hi>Three Years,</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> being the <hi>Accompliſhing</hi> to <hi>Scatter,</hi> and ſo carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>wearing out</hi> of the Saints ſo much further then the <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Half,</hi> or 1260 Years; even unto the 3 Years and <hi>Half,</hi> Firſt of the 30; and then their Remainder Unites with the laſt 45 in <hi>Finiſhing;</hi> For as I have ſhewn, there can be no Diſtance between in the 1335 of <hi>Scattering</hi> and <hi>Finiſhing.</hi> And the whole 1335 are Joyn'd, as lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by various Delays and Appearances, ſince eſpecially the laſt <hi>Half Time</hi> of the <hi>Reformation;</hi> to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt. And this is an Artifice of the Divine
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105101:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> Hand of Scripture moſt Curious and Admirable. And the ſame both Equipoize and Artifice, are alſo moſt Conſpicuous in the 1260 <hi>Days</hi> of <hi>Years,</hi> and the <hi>Three Days</hi> and <hi>Half of Tears,</hi> Rev. 11. Theſe 3 <hi>Days and Half</hi> Hold the only Poſſible Addition of Time beyond the 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> or <hi>Three Times and a Half</hi> for <hi>Accompliſhing</hi> to <hi>Scatter;</hi> For we find no other Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ſpace of Time Mentioned either in <hi>Daniel,</hi> or the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that can be ſo much as ſuppoſed to lie at the End of the 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> and <hi>before the Seventh Trumpet,</hi> Except theſe <hi>Days</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> alone; But theſe with all Harmony and <hi>Symmetry</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> are Placed there; For they are Scituated near to the 1260 <hi>Days</hi> to give a <hi>Mantiſſa,</hi> or Surpluſage of Time to them, for the <hi>Accompliſhing</hi> the <hi>Scattering</hi> and <hi>wearing</hi> out the <hi>Holy People,</hi> that had been During their whole Space; And they muſt be as near the <hi>Seventh Trumpet,</hi> becauſe the Holy Spirit is Expreſs; Immediately upon the <hi>Accompliſhing to Scatter, The Wonders ſhall be Finiſhed;</hi> And he is as Expreſs, <hi>The Seventh Trumpet is the Trumpet of Finiſhing;</hi> For when the <hi>Seventh Angel begins to ſound,</hi> The <hi>Myſtery of God ſhall be Finiſhed,</hi> as he hath <hi>Evangeliz'd by all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, the Prophets.</hi> Thus as in <hi>Daniel,</hi> The <hi>Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>to Scatter</hi> lies between the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> of <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Saints,</hi> and the <hi>Finiſhing Wonders; So in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> the <hi>Three Days</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> lie between the 1260 <hi>Days</hi> of the <hi>Sackcloth Prophecy</hi> (which are alſo <hi>Three Times and a Half,)</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Seventh Trumpet</hi> of <hi>Finiſhing;</hi> And they muſt be One either with the 1260 or with the Firſt of thoſe <hi>Thirty</hi> making 1260, 1290; Or elſe they could have no Room; For the Divine Spirit Claſping 1260 ſo cloſe, as to make it imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately 1290; There can come in no <hi>Three Years</hi> and a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105101:32"/> 
                  <hi>Half</hi> poſſibly between, that is not United with one of the Numbers; Which is even <hi>Arithmetic</hi> Demonſtration.</p>
               <p>But now as to the Equipoize of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> It muſt be Acknowledg'd, that before the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Determin'd the contrary, the <hi>Three Days</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> might have been Intended to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated with the 1260 <hi>Days</hi> of the <hi>Sackcloth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſts</hi> Victory over the <hi>Witneſſes;</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering to the <hi>Three Times</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> of the 1260 <hi>Days</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> The <hi>Witneſſes</hi> and the <hi>Woman</hi> being one; and the <hi>Sackcloth,</hi> Being <hi>Overcome, Kill'd, worn out, Scattered,</hi> the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> State being one, as to the main Intention alſo; Only the Deepeſt Time of Sufferings expreſs'd by one more then the other; and ſo the <hi>Three Days</hi> and <hi>Half;</hi> the <hi>Three Times</hi> and <hi>Half,</hi> the two 1260 <hi>Days</hi> had been all one Time, and had begun and ended together. And I muſt Ereely, and Humbly Confeſs, This was my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and my hope it would be ſo, although I had always a Jealous Eye upon theſe <hi>three Days</hi> and <hi>Half.</hi> But nothing but Event could Determine to the other ſide, The Ballance of <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſtands ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven concerning the Caſe; And indeed if <hi>Ninety Seven,</hi> as I affirm, and ſee no Reaſon to Retract, be the end of the 1260 Days; It muſt needs be, that when the <hi>Three Days</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> have done the Service of <hi>Three Times</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> Coequal with the whole 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> and pointing to a deepeſt Time of Suffering, and ſo Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling one another; The latter then do the Service of an <hi>Epitome,</hi> a <hi>Mantiſſa,</hi> a Recollection of the whole, and Run ſo far as upon the <hi>Three</hi> Firſt <hi>Years</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> of the <hi>Thirty,</hi> which Thirty, are Principally for <hi>Finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> And though they ſuffer the Cloud of the <hi>Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> Summ'd up <hi>Scattering,</hi> Yet they are Recompens'd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105101:33"/> with the Glory of the Conſtellation of Great and Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Events at their <hi>Riſing;</hi> Now the <hi>Three Days</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> doing this Manifold Service, and bearing this variety of Aſpects, is moſt uſual in Scriptures Improvement of its <hi>Types,</hi> ſo that I need not Inſiſt further on it.</p>
               <p>I will give only one Inſtance in a Caſe of near Affinity with this; The Three <hi>Hundred Ninety</hi> Years <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 4.</note> of <hi>Ezekiels Bearing the Iniquity</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Iſrael,</hi> gave the very <hi>Chronological</hi> ſpace from the Death of <hi>Solomon</hi> to <hi>Ezekiels Temple;</hi> It firſt ſet out the Sin of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the <hi>Ten Tribes</hi> making Defection from the <hi>Houſe of David;</hi> and then turns, as it were back, and ſettles the ſtandard of <hi>Prophetic</hi> Time a Day for a Year, as an <hi>Epitomizing</hi> of <hi>Prophetic</hi> Time to the very <hi>End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To Summ up this Point of Diſcourſe then, I look upon the End of the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half,</hi> or 1260 Days of Years, as the moſt Unmoveable Reſt of the <hi>Three Years</hi> and <hi>Half;</hi> And that, They are but as a Summary and Recollection of them, or a little Surpluſage added to them; And that the 1260 Ended at 97. And, That Ninety Seven began in the <hi>Autumnal Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nox,</hi> of what we Generally Count 98 but in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetic Calendar;</hi> 97 Juſt Ending; I therefore as before, ſo now again give the Account from 97 and to Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Eight in the ſame <hi>Prophetic</hi> Style one Year; To 99 is Two Years; To 1700 ſtill in the ſame <hi>Prophetic</hi> Style is Three Years, <hi>viz.</hi> at each <hi>Autumnal Equinox;</hi> and at the <hi>Vernal Equinox</hi> of 1700 ending, in Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Account, but in Prophetical the Half of 1700.</p>
               <p>The Laſt Half Year of the Three Years and a Half will Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire then, in the very Middle of the Year, at the <hi>Vernal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinox,</hi> The Time of our Lords Reſurrection; Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105101:33"/> I Humbly hope, with mighty Effects of it, in the <hi>Riſing</hi> again of the Glory of the Goſpel, the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and all the People of Chriſt ſo long lying Dead in the Breadth of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and its <hi>Antichriſtian Papacy</hi> then beginning to be <hi>Judg'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have now with all Humble Reverence of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracles, <hi>Covering</hi> as it were my <hi>Face,</hi> whatever of Light and Under<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>anding God hath given me, as yet not Able to behold their Glory; And my <hi>Feet</hi> in the ſenſe of my Unworthyneſs and Great Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Imperfections in Knowing, or <hi>Prophecying;</hi> I have yet with <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Godly Fear</hi> ſhewn; That there is a Frame of <hi>Prophecy</hi> Curiouſly and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully made; By which Inſenſibly (however cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly foreknown to God, which way every Thing would come to paſs;) the Great Events ſhould with ſuch an Equal Ballance be made Inclinable to 97 or 1700; That Providence ſhould with the Truth of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as it ſaw Fitt, Determine upon either at the very Time; I come therefore to the Fourth Head propos'd; <hi>Viz.</hi> To conſider the Reaſons of the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Great Events, to have been Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected at 97, from thence to 1700.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Head. 4th.</hi> The Tranſlation of the Great Effects <hi>of Prophecy;</hi> The <hi>Accompliſhing</hi> to <hi>Scatter</hi> the <hi>Power of the Holy People;</hi> the <hi>Riſing</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes;</hi> and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to <hi>Finiſh Wonders;</hi> have been Tranſlated from 97, and are Humbly to be expected, e're the End of 1700, on this Threefold Account.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Principally, and in the Firſt place by way of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraction,</hi> or what Scripture is pleaſed to call; Gods <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>Promiſe;</hi> or <hi>Repenting</hi> of the <hi>Good</hi> he ſaid, He would <hi>Benefit his People</hi> with, at ſuch a Time; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jreme.</hi> 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10.</note> We know in ſtrict ſenſe; The Faithful God, who
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105101:34"/> notwithſtanding our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> cannot <hi>deny</hi> himſelf cannot Break promiſe, nor can any of his Predictions Fail; Yet he knows how ſo to order Things, that the Sin of his Servants ſhould be under ſuch an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Providence,</hi> as if both <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes</hi> did fail for the Puniſhment of their Unbeleif, and Diſobedience, and Unſuitable Frame.</p>
               <p>I have Reaſon therefore more to bewail the Diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable Frame of my own, and other the Hearts of thoſe who are called <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and the <hi>Reformed;</hi> in not being more Ready for thoſe Great Effects at the Time, then the being miſtaken i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Explanation of <hi>Pr,ophecy,</hi> and the <hi>Prophetic</hi> Numbers, or even the Determination upon <hi>Ninety Seven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For it is moſt Evident, God hath Reſerved to himſelf a Prerogative of <hi>Pronouncing Evil,</hi> very poſſitively, as in the Caſe of <hi>Nineveh;</hi> Jonah. 3d. <hi>Yet Fourty Days,</hi> and <hi>Nineveh</hi> ſhall be <hi>deſtroyed;</hi> And yet God ſeeing their <hi>Turning from their Evil</hi> ways, alſo <hi>Repented of the Evil, that he thought to do unto them;</hi> So on the other ſide, he makes a ſeeming <hi>Breach of Promiſe</hi> in Delay of the <hi>Good, he intended</hi> at ſuch a Time; And yet as I have before Argued in <hi>Nathan;</hi> So it is plain no Blame could <hi>lie on Jonah</hi> for the miſtake of Time, but for his too high Reſentment of the Diſhonour, as he Apprehended on himſelf, of being Accounted a <hi>Falſe Prophet;</hi> However God Juſtified him, not long after by the Irrepealable <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Ninevehs</hi> utter De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by <hi>Zephaniah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Delay, or Tranſlation of the Great Effects of Viſion from 97 to 1700, I Impute therefore in the Firſt place to <hi>Infraction,</hi> or Gods <hi>Breach of Promiſe,</hi> with Great Aſſurance and Boldneſs of Speech, as to the manner of Expreſſion; Becauſe God hath been pleas'd
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105101:34"/> to uſe it, elſe I ſhould not have Dared make uſe of it; and then as to the Thing it ſelf, I am Bold becauſe I Find ſo Great Reaſons for 97, as the moſt Central Time of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> and ſuch Fair Delineations, and ſo Curious a Hand of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> Reſerving a Liberty and Freedom of ſo Uniting 1700 within it, as Providential Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Juſtice, by way of <hi>Infraction</hi> or <hi>Abrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Or Wiſdom in a way of Mercy and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Illuſtration of Vengeance on the Enemies of the People of God, ſaw Fit. To give therefore a more full Account of <hi>Infraction,</hi> or <hi>Breach of Promiſe,</hi> I would offer my Apprehenſion with all Humility and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and yet with Uprightneſs and Sincerity; I ſay therefore, God had by the <hi>Prophecys</hi> of his word Pointed to 97, as the Ending of the <hi>Sackcloth</hi> of the <hi>Witneſs Prophecy,</hi> in their <hi>Prophecy</hi> Fulfil'd in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> and of other the Great Effects but with a Conditional Reſerve, if there were a Suitable Frame in the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> both the Sufferers and the more ſelf-Subſiſtent <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> under <hi>Reformed</hi> Princes, Nations, and their Laws: I ſay, If there were a Frame and Activity Suitable to ſo Great a Revolution; Such a Frame as Agrees with the <hi>Spirit of Life from God,</hi> with their <hi>ſtanding on their Feet,</hi> with their Appearing <hi>with the Lamb on Mount Zion, having</hi> the <hi>Fathers Name written on their Foreheads;</hi> But there was not ſuch a Frame among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of any Diſtinction, or Denoml<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, of any Title, Order, or Degree; Hereupon Riſes the Lords <hi>Breach of Promiſe;</hi> For in the Room of ſuch a <hi>Spirit of Life,</hi> the <hi>Sardian State</hi> lies heavy upon the whole; <hi>They have a Name to Live,</hi> and yet are <hi>Dead;</hi> They do not <hi>Fill up the Things</hi> that <hi>Remain,</hi> and are in order to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> They are in a very <hi>Sleepy,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwatchful</hi> Temper, as to the <hi>coming of</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:105101:35"/> Chriſt; ſo that it is like to <hi>come upon them,</hi> at an <hi>Hour, they know not.</hi> When the <hi>Lord ſaw this, it diſpleaſed Him;</hi> then ſaid He, <hi>they ſhall know my Breach of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe:</hi> What I had Determin'd at 97, ſhall be as a Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Delay. If they had been in a Condition to have <hi>Smitten,</hi> as often as they <hi>would,</hi> with a high Impulſe of <hi>Will</hi> the <hi>Antichriſtian Earth</hi> with <hi>Plagues;</hi> to have Shot with all the <hi>Arrows</hi> of the <hi>Lord's Deliverance;</hi> their <hi>Accompliſhment to Scatter,</hi> ſhould have immediately commenc'd with <hi>Finiſhing of Wonders.</hi> But even the Suffering Part of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and much more the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, being found in the Condition before deſcrib'd (without any Reflection on the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes); It looks, as if in <hi>David's Numbering the People;</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> was <hi>Diſpleaſed,</hi> and left him under Effectual Motives ſo to <hi>Number,</hi> which brought a Plague on All; So God, Provoked Juſtly with the Univerſal Declination of the <hi>Reformation</hi> from His Truth, and the Purity of His Worſhip, and the Holineſs of His Ways, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew that Spirit of Zeal, Courage, and Reſolution in the Cauſe, and Intereſt of God, His Goſpel and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; His <hi>Spirit</hi> not <hi>coming</hi> upon them, as on the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of Old: Nor was He pleaſed to give them that Reſolution, To make no Peace, without the Security and Freedom for that which they accounted the True Chriſtian Religion; or with them, who would, and do now, make Advantage of that Peace, to the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and Slavery of them, with whom they are, or ought to be, of the ſame Character; <hi>who keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God,</hi> and <hi>hold the Teſtimony of Jeſus.</hi> So that this Peace was not at all to their Honour, before God, and His Servants; although thoſe under them ought to be Humbled, becauſe their want of Faith, Love, Holineſs, Peace, and Union, ſo Diſhonoured
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105101:35"/> God, that He, in Juſt Offence, left Princes, States, Governments to themſelves, not to Appear for God, as for their own Intereſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>Object. I know it may be ſaid, Becauſe the Time was not come, <hi>There was not that</hi> Spirit <hi>of</hi> Life from God <hi>foretold by</hi> Prophecy <hi>coming upon them; and therefore they could not Act according to it: And this alone was Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enough,</hi> Ninety Seven <hi>was not the Time of</hi> Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing <hi>to</hi> Scatter, <hi>nor of Beginning to</hi> Finiſh the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is moſt True; the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Life from God,</hi> not coming down, and <hi>Entering</hi> the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> did ſhew, It was not the Time: But it is yet True, the unſuitable Frame of Spirit in <hi>Proteſtants</hi> did Provoke God to <hi>Breach of Promiſe;</hi> the culpable Cauſe of Mercies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd or delay'd, is the want of that Holy Agreeable Frame, although the Gift of ſuch Grace is from God; For in <hi>God alone is our Help;</hi> yet ſtill <hi>our Deſtruction is of our ſelves.</hi> It is alway His Spirit, that makes that <hi>other</hi> Spirit in us, that was in <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua:</hi> The want of ſuch a Spirit, as is Agreeable to what God hath promiſed to do, provokes Him moſt Juſtly to <hi>Breach of Promiſe,</hi> as to the Time held out to our Eye; although he alone Gives that <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> at the very Time, when the Promiſe muſt and ſhall certainly be Fulfilled. Want of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> is a full Reaſon of Want of <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;</hi> although at the Time when <hi>Deliverance</hi> ſhall be, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lineſs</hi> ſhall be alſo: The peculiar Frame agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Kingdom of Chriſt is the Frame, we find <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obab.</hi> 17.</note> in the Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> not in our <hi>Sardis.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us now Conſider the Delay, or Tranſlation of the great Effects expected at 97, from 97 to 1700, as the word <hi>Breach of Promiſe</hi> ſignifies <hi>Abruption,</hi> or <hi>Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> off the <hi>Series,</hi> and Contexture, God had pleaſed to
<pb facs="tcp:105101:36"/> have Begun, and ſeem'd to be Going on in; as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot but be acknowledged, There was not in 97, the glorious Appearance of the expected Effects; So on the other ſide, it cannot be deny'd, There were ſuch Beginnings, that if God had pleaſed to go on in, there had certainly been, before this Time, a very great Change and <hi>Revolution</hi> in the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But no ſooner were thoſe Offertures made, but God ſhew'd his <hi>Abru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi> or Breaking off from any Thing he had Begun; Two great Inſtances of which, we had in that Year.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The Treaty of Peace at <hi>Reſwick,</hi> was a very Remarkable Diſpoſe of God, bringing the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Princes to a Neceſſity of making Peace, while <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes</hi> and States had a Ballance upon them and the Peace. This looked very Hopefully, that the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> and the <hi>Reformation,</hi> wherein the Glory of God, of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Safety of His People, and their Peace and Quiet, was ſo undeniably Compriz'd, ſhould have found great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages; and by an Embarraſſement on all further <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution</hi> on <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> there might have been an <hi>Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment</hi> of <hi>Scattering.</hi> This was a gracious Honorary Diſpoſe on 97; and at the very <hi>Autumnal Equinox,</hi> as the very Time, that was to bear the Signal of the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Riſing.</hi> Herein God was pleaſed to <hi>ſet Judgment</hi> before thoſe <hi>Proteſtant Sovereigns,</hi> and to ſhew them what they were to do; eſpecially, conſidering what Juſt Pleas they had to Inſiſt upon, as particularly and eminently that <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Nantz,</hi> in behalf of the <hi>French Reformed,</hi> where the Perſecution hath ſince been Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued with ſo great Barbarity.</p>
               <p>But to ſhew God's <hi>Abruption,</hi> as in the very Time, and in the very Act of the Treaty concluded, and ſo his <hi>Infraction</hi> in the very Year of <hi>Ninety Seven,</hi> and of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105101:36"/> the Peace concluded. And to Remonſtrate both, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Nations about, as he hath ſometimes put a Word into the Mouth of his very Enemies, eſpecially when they are of Eminency; as <hi>Balaam,</hi> an exalted <hi>Prophet; Caiaphas,</hi> the High-Prieſt: So it is much to be Reflected upon, what the <hi>King of France,</hi> that Prince of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> writ to the <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Paris</hi> in the beginning of the Month called <hi>January,</hi> in Popiſh <hi>Style</hi> 98, but in True <hi>Prophetic</hi> and even <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Style 97: Requiring the Thankſgiving of <hi>Te Deum</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Manner for the Peace, thus He Began; <hi>The Time, which Heaven hath Ordained</hi> (How expreſs for 97.) <hi>for the Reconciliation of the Nations; Sure the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of each Nation made up the Nations.</hi> This looked Fair for the <hi>Accompliſhing</hi> to <hi>Scatter;</hi> For the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> making up the <hi>Nations,</hi> and the Time for the Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of the Nations being come, their <hi>Scattering</hi> or Perſecution was to Ceaſe, or to be <hi>Accompliſhed,</hi> How elſe Reconciled!</p>
               <p>But as if at the ſame Time God made an <hi>Abruption</hi> upon what was ſo promiſingly Begun in 97, and put a Reproof into that Prince's Mouth, upon the <hi>Proteſtant Princes,</hi> and in them upon the <hi>Nations,</hi> and even the <hi>Churches;</hi> walking ſo much beneath the True Spirit of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> and ſo provoking God to withdraw His mighty Spirit and Preſence from the Princes: That King thus expreſſes himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That which I Glory in moſt of all, is, the Worſhip of the true Religion, as Authorized by a ſolemn Treaty under So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns of a Different Faith; the Author of ſo many Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhews Himſelf too manifeſtly not to be Acknowledged; and the Viſible Characters of his Almighty Hand, which they Bear, ſeem to be the Seal, he hath Affixed to them to Juſtify my Intentions; Buſied from this Time forward in</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:105101:37"/> 
                  <hi>Cauſing him to be truly Worſhipped in all my Dominions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all which, I have not the leaſt Regard to the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings of that Haughty Monarch, in which there is much of the Spirit, and Style of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Aſſyria</hi>'s Letter by <hi>Rabſhakeh;</hi> when he ask'd, <hi>Am I come up without</hi> Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah? All I conſider is, What of Agreement there can be Found, between His Words, and the Words of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> As when he ſaith, The <hi>Time</hi> for the <hi>Reconciliation</hi> of the <hi>Nations is Come;</hi> a Word of great Extent in Scripture-Senſe, and Introducting a great Change indeed among the Nations, and very Conſonant to Scripture Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; For I have all Reaſons of Aſſurance to Conclude, It was ſo in the Firſt Inſtitution of God, and the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Peace was a Fit Method in Human View to it: When the Treaty therefore was Concluded, and a Peace, ſo call'd, made without Reconciliation of the Nations, in that great Intereſt of the People of God, the Freedom and Peace of the <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>France, Piedmont, Savoy,</hi> the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and other Parts; and He Himſelf the Principal Perſecutor, under the miſerable Bigotry of Thinking, He <hi>Does God Good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, in Perſecuting,</hi> as the Tenor of his Letter Imports; wherein he Appears <hi>Drunk</hi> with the <hi>Wine</hi> of <hi>Babyloniſh Fornication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Another Inſtance of Divine <hi>Abruption,</hi> and ſo of <hi>Inſraction,</hi> in the ſame Year, was that Monumental Victory over the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Army and the <hi>Ottoman Sultan</hi> in Perſon with it. Now ſeeing, That Tyranny more immediately preſſes the <hi>Grecian</hi> Profeſſors of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and Hath laid them under ſo great Slavery, and Darkneſs; This Eaſtern Part of the Chriſtian Church Falling into a like Superſtitious Ignorance, Any True Servants of God among them, were carried as with the other of the Two <hi>Wings</hi> into a <hi>Wilderneſs-State,</hi> and fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Re.</hi> 12. 14.</note>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:105101:37"/> great Darkneſs from the Light and Purity of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and ſo into Slavery under <hi>Mahometan Impoſture</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and thus have continued to this Day; And in how <hi>Lethargic,</hi> or rather a State of Death; All thoſe, whom we call the <hi>Greek Churches,</hi> or <hi>Grecian</hi> Chriſtians do at this Time lie, None that know them can be Ignorant, There being only Remainders and the Ruins of thoſe Ancient Churches, even as of their Cities.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Propheſies</hi> and Promiſes of Scripture Reach, yet unto them; and at that very Year 97. Accordingly therefore about the ſame <hi>Autumnal Equinox</hi> of it; It pleaſed Infinite Wiſdom, and Goodneſs to Arm with a Mighty Power and Spirit the <hi>Imperial</hi> Army, and the Leaders of it; and to give them a very Monumental Victory, even a Victory, like as in the Day of <hi>Mid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or upon any other of the Ancient Enemies of the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to their Greateſt Conſternation, and the Breaking all their Meaſures and Deſigns; Hereto Add, what God was pleas'd not far from the ſame Time to do by the <hi>Czar of Moſcovy,</hi> a Prince of the very <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Profeſſion of Chriſtianity; Theſe Victoriouſneſſes had undoubtedly been carryed to the very Gates of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> Had there been but that <hi>Spirit of Life</hi> from God upon them! But all lying in that Dead State; The <hi>Emperor</hi> in the very <hi>God</hi> of Popiſh <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſm</hi> and the <hi>Bond</hi> of that Evil; The <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in all the Superſtition and Blindneſs of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; There was then Firſt Gods <hi>Infraction</hi> as to the Year 97: The Great and Complemental Effects ſhone not to expectation that Year as Light Day: And therefore there was an <hi>Abruption,</hi> a Breaking off that Series and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture God had began; So all is laid ſtill in a Peace between the <hi>Port</hi> and the <hi>Empire;</hi> and a Truce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105101:38"/> the <hi>Ottoman</hi> and <hi>Moſcovian</hi> Princes; Which how God will Diſpoſe of, we are yet to obſerve in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Courſe of Providence. Diſpoſes of God with Relation to the <hi>Ottoman Signiory</hi> are the more to be obſerved on theſe Great <hi>Prophetic</hi> Conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It pleaſed the Divine Spirit to place the very opening of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Finiſhing of Wonders</hi> on that <hi>Mahometane Potentacy coming to its End,</hi> and none to help it. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. Laſt with <hi>C.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Grecian</hi> Churches, as we Style them, Are the ſad Remains of thoſe <hi>Seven Apoclyptic Churh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> made the <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Emblems</hi> of all Chriſtian Churches till the Glory of the New <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> And therefore from the Time of that given; However under ſuch a Rejection Now, Yet, are <hi>Beloved for the Fathers ſakes,</hi> I mean Thoſe <hi>Primitive Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Hour,</hi> the <hi>Day,</hi> the <hi>Month,</hi> the <hi>Year</hi> allowed to the <hi>Turkiſh Empire</hi> to ſtand Arm'd and in <hi>Procinctu</hi> Reaches <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.</note> Juſt to 97: as hath been by other <hi>Apocalyptic</hi> Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as by my ſelf <hi>Leſs than the Leaſt, made out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. From the paſſing away of the <hi>Second</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh Woe,</hi> That great, and Bleſſed Sound Commences. <hi>The</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Kingdoms of this World are Become the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt;</hi> But as <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> came firſt, as a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.</note> Judgment on the <hi>Latine,</hi> as it is to be Diſtinctly call'd, or <hi>Weſtern Antichriſtianiſm;</hi> So it is to be Preferr'd in the Expectation of Judgment Firſt upon it ſelf; That ſo <hi>Tyrannous</hi> a <hi>Pſeudo-Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiſm</hi> that came upon it, may not be Removed before the <hi>Provocati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> of the Sin Oh how much Reaſon have we then to cry to Heaven for that <hi>Spirit of Life</hi> upon us all; I hope, I much more Deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re it upon my ſelf, then the Honour of being a True <hi>Prophet</hi> concerning it, If one could be Separated from the other.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:105101:38"/>
               <p> Although I am afraid to defer any thing to <hi>Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtry,</hi> I cannot yet but Juſt Mention; That, That ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable, even <hi>Phrenetic</hi> Superſtition of the <hi>Turkiſh Proceſſion,</hi> was order'd on the Firſt New Moon in the Month called <hi>Decemb.</hi> 97. and fell out on its Third Day.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Proceſſion</hi> was a Publick Declaration, Their Affairs were come to Extremity; Their Deprecation of the Diſpleaſure of Heaven ſo Vehemently, ſpoke an Apprehenſion of the Tottering, and Ruine of their <hi>Port</hi> and <hi>Empire.</hi> Thus Providence Diſcover'd, what was in the Womb of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> if there had not been an <hi>Abruption;</hi> And that <hi>Abruption</hi> ſhew'd it ſelf, in that, So great a Victory was not made an Advance to further Victoriouſneſs, and even Ruine of that <hi>Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed I cannot but make a Paralell of it, with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 16. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Moabs</hi> wearying himſelf on <hi>his High Place,</hi> and then coming <hi>to his Sanctuary to pray.</hi> And the <hi>word of the Lord</hi> ſince, and <hi>from that Time</hi> is, That within <hi>Three Years</hi> as exactly Numbred, as the Days of an <hi>Hireling,</hi> and the <hi>Glory of the Ottoman Power ſhall be Contemned; And all that great Multitude and the Remnant ſhall be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Small and feeble.</hi> Now theſe Three Years are to be Accounted to End in the Month <hi>December</hi> in the Year 1700.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Objec.</hi> But may there not be on continuing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, and Unpreparedneſs for Mercy, a further <hi>Infraction</hi> and <hi>Abruption,</hi> even at the Year 1700.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By That Scituation of the Three Years and a Half between the 1260, and the <hi>Seventh Trumpet,</hi> and the ſo cloſely Conterminating on each; and <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſo expreſs and poſitive therein; That it ſhould be Subjected to any ſuch Ballance of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> is utterly Impoſſible; For though when there is an <hi>Equilibration</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:105101:39"/> 
                  <hi>of Prophecy,</hi> there <hi>Providence,</hi> does, as it ſees fit, although all way in it ſelf Determin'd; Yet where <hi>Prophecy</hi> is Peremptory and Abſolute, <hi>Providence</hi> alway Acts ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it; And ſo it is here, that there can be no Fear of an <hi>Infraction</hi> or an <hi>Abruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus diſcours'd the delay according to the Scripture words, Gods <hi>Infraction</hi> and <hi>Abruption;</hi> For he is pleas'd ſo to Style it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>My Breach;</hi> The True and Faithful God takes ſuch a Prerogative to ſpeak his Intentions of Grace at ſuch a Time, under the Reſervation of a Condition, That there ſhould be a Suitable Agreeable Frame in his People to his <hi>Promiſes;</hi> Or elſe a further Time Reſerved; But as I have made out, there is alſo a further Reſerved Time for Wiſe and Holy Reaſons in a way of Grace, in the Retirements of Prophetic Senſe; And ſo I cannot but hope, There is at this Time That Wiſe, Holy and Gracious Purpoſe of the Delay; That the very Juſt Seaſon of the Judgment on <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſhould be taken ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what hath been already laid down, and needs no Repetition, that ſhall alſo concur with thoſe of Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>Viz.</hi> The <hi>Popiſh Jubilee,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing, according to what I have Humbly laid down; The <hi>Prophecys</hi> of Scripture have plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing beyond theſe <hi>Three Years</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> ending with the Year 1700; but the <hi>Finiſhing Wonders</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Seventh Trumpet of Finiſhing in the Revelation:</hi> As I have moſt Abaſed Senſe of my own Weakneſs, Darkneſs, and Unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſs; and Profoundeſt Reverence of the Divine Wiſdom, Holineſs, Supreme Dominion; In which Regard none can ſtand before him, or <hi>as a Shepherd appoint</hi> him the <hi>Time;</hi> So I cannot but Truſt in his Mercy, and the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghtineſs of his Arm, He will bring it at that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Time to paſs; and I obſerve; That in Callenging of any <hi>Shepherd</hi> to <hi>ſtand before him,</hi> he eſpecially Directs to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105101:39"/> thoſe, who, when they hear of the Judgments of God on the Enemies of his People; <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Babylon;</hi> and So now on <hi>Babiloniſh Rome,</hi> think; They can bring up <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 50.</note> thoſe, who ſhall Oppoſe the Councels of God, like a <hi>Lyon coming up from the Swellings of Jordan</hi> with all ſpeedy Rage and Power, and oblige him to chooſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Time for the Execution of his Judgment; Theſe are <note place="margin">Jer.</note> they, who would ſtand as <hi>Shepherds</hi> before him, and <hi>appoint him a</hi> Time; Not they, who would <hi>wait upon him in the way</hi> of his <hi>Judgments,</hi> and would Diſcern the <hi>Signs</hi> of the <hi>Times</hi> thereof; For it is a Severe Reproof; The <hi>Stork in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens knoweth her Appointed Time,</hi> and the <hi>Crane</hi> and the <hi>Swallow</hi> and the <hi>Turtle obſerve, But my People know not the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerem.</hi> 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Judgment of the Lord. Surely the Prophetic Scribe;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Accounting the Numbers Time it ſets; <hi>He made it in vain,</hi> the <hi>Pen</hi> of that <hi>Scribe is in vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, the Apoſtle does moſt Vehemently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Theſ.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> not to be moved with <hi>Letter,</hi> or <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Word,</hi> as if the <hi>Day of Chriſt</hi> were at <hi>Hand;</hi> But then at that Time He gives the moſt certain Subſtantial Line of Time in General to it; <hi>Viz.</hi> The Courſe of the <hi>Son of Perdition,</hi> till he <hi>goes into Perdition;</hi> And then the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> very particularly gives the Definite ſpace of Time, his <hi>Forty Two Moons</hi> of Years, that we may know how to Diſtribute betwixt the Too Great Suddenneſs, or the Too Long Delay of the Expectation, and yet throughout to maintain that <hi>Looking for and haſting on to the Day of God</hi> in all Holy Deſires, and Preparation by Suitable Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, while we daily Conſider; How he hath <hi>Declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> the <hi>End from the Beginning,</hi> that we may ſee and <hi>behold it together,</hi> and be <hi>ſtruck</hi> with <hi>Admiration;</hi> This is that Glorious Challenge, God makes upon the <hi>Idols</hi> of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> in Juſtification of himſelf againſt,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105101:40"/> them, <hi>Declare, Shew to us the Things, that are to come, Do,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 41. 23. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Work Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> Judgments, or Deliverances; that <hi>we may know, you are Gods;</hi> To attend our God therefore herein, in ſearching out, and declaring what he hath firſt declar'd, is to give Glory to him; And this is the only End I have through his Grace propos'd in this <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 41. 13. &amp;c.</note> Diſcourſe; In its Beginning, By ſetting out the certainty of <hi>Babylons Judgment,</hi> at the Times of its Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Solemnity, of Pomp and Pride; and of the Strongeſt Combination of the <hi>Horns</hi> of the Beaſt, the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> to ſtrengthen, and exalt it; and for the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Servants of God, who will not <hi>Receive</hi> his <hi>Mark,</hi> nor <hi>Worſhip his Image.</hi> Now that in this Time, its <hi>Plagues</hi> may <hi>come upon</hi> that <hi>City of Fornications, Drunk</hi> with the <hi>Blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> as in one <hi>Day;</hi> I cannot but Humbly Beſeech, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it to all the Servants of God, who Love the Appearing and Kingdom of Chriſt, not to be Diſcourag'd with the Delay beyond 97; but to cry with the <hi>Spirit and the Bride: Come Lord Jeſus come Quickly:</hi> knowing the Time ſo undoubtedly Fixed, and ſo near Herein,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <salute>The Grace of our Lord Jeſus be with you all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>Books lately Printed and Sold by <hi>John Marſhall,</hi> at the <hi>Bible in Grace-Church-street.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon on the Death of the Reverend Divine Mr. <hi>Thomas Gouge.</hi> Who Deceaſed <hi>Jan. 18th</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>99. By <hi>John Neſsbit</hi> one of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Lecturers at <hi>Pinners-Hall, Breadſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The Government of the Thoughts Prefactory to the Government of the Tongue, by the Author of the Duty of Man.</p>
            <p>An Ellegiack Eſſay on the Pious Memory of that Eminent and Learned Divine Mr. <hi>Mathew Mead,</hi> with his True Effiges newly Engrav'd to the Life, alſo moſt of his Works with moſt ſorts of Books to Learn Short-hand.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:40"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105101:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
